Directionless? Scientists Offer Some Clues

So I'm walking down Lexington Avenue in Manhattan on a gorgeous Saturday afternoon, and I stop to admire a church that I'd never really noticed before: St. Jean Baptiste, on the corner of 76th Street.
I like its noble neo-classical fussiness, its four foliated white marble pillars and two towers stacked with arches, columns, crowns. I dart inside for a look, gaze up at the painted dome, breathe in the rich, churchy air, and go back out to continue my walk downtown.
It's warm, I'm thirsty, so after about 10 blocks I cross Lexington Avenue to buy a bottle of juice from a grocery. I drink the juice as I stroll along, and soon I stop to admire another lovely church. Four white marble pillars, dome, double towers.
How can it be, I ask myself, that there are two such similar and ornate churches on Lexington Avenue, and that I, a lover of architecture and longtime New Yorker, hadn't realized it? I run up to the entrance to explore this second interior, but stop short in horror when I read the sign: St. Jean Baptiste. Holy deja vu all over again! With considerable self-disgust, I reconstruct what happened. The simple act of crossing Lexington Avenue for refreshments had completely flipped around my sense of left, right, north and south, with the result that, after leaving the grocery, I had mindlessly retraced my steps back uptown.
Some women are attracted to the wrong men; I'm attracted to the wrong direction. I get lost driving, I get lost walking, I get lost in the great outdoors, I get lost in corridors.  A boyfriend once observed that my internal compass was so dysfunctional as to be almost useful: watch which way Natalie turns, and then head in the opposite direction.
I've found some comfort in the fact that many others suffer from my little handicap. Not for nothing have ''global positioning systems'' become one of the most popular frills in automobiles. The mere mention of ''poor sense of direction'' in an Ann Landers column invariably unleashes a floodtide of reader confessionals, tragicomic tales of getting lost on the way to weddings, funerals, the delivery room.
More heartening still is the keen interest that scientists have lately taken in the subject of how humans and other species navigate -- or fail to. The study of what they call spatial cognition, or way-finding, is attracting a growing cadre of researchers from all sectors of the academic map, including psychology, neuroscience, computer science, zoology, anthropology, linguistics and geography.
''I've been in this business long enough to see my specialty go in and out of style, and back in again,'' said Dr. Gary L. Allen, a psychology professor at the University of South Carolina in Columbia. ''Right now, spatial cognition studies are extremely popular, and they're more interdisciplinary than ever.''
Some scientists are delving into the talents of the world's great wanderers: birds, turtles, caribou and other creatures that travel thousands upon thousands of miles a year without once forgetting where they parked the car. Other researchers are zeroing in on the specific parts of the brain that allow travelers to use spatial layout or visible landmarks to guide their paths -- the mind's placemakers, if you will. It turns out that the brain is a compulsive categorizer and pigeonholer, in orienting itself topographically as much as in sizing up new acquaintances or judging ethnic groups.
In a review that will appear in September in the British journal Brain, Dr. Geoffrey Aguirre, a neuroscientist at the University of Pennsylvania, describes a group of patients who, as a result of stroke or brain injury, suffer from an unusual and eerily specific type of topographic disorientation. He calls it ''landmark agnosia'' -- an inability to recognize big, stable objects in the environment, particularly buildings. Such patients can describe where it is they need to go, but when they are outside, they cannot use the most salient landmarks -- a neighbor's yellow house, the local supermarket -- to anchor and direct them.
''They'll turn a corner,'' Dr. Aguirre said in an interview, ''and the street will be completely unfamiliar to them.''
Over time, the patients learn to compensate for their discrete deficit. ''They pay attention to minor details in the environment that most of us are unaware of,'' Dr. Aguirre said. ''They may notice a particular doorknob on a building they've passed, or the number of slats in a park bench. By focusing on these tiny features, they manage to string together a path.''
The patients were known to have lesions in an area of the lower back portion of brain called the lingual gyrus. ''The general model for this area of the brain is that it has a number of specialized modules for recognizing different objects,'' Dr. Aguirre said. ''So you can have agnosias where you can't recognize faces, or farmers with damage here may have a sheep or cow agnosia.''
Through neuro-imaging studies of normal people, Dr. Aguirre has found that when subjects are presented with a series of pictures, the right lingual gyrus fires most avidly in response to images of buildings, and barely at all when viewing pictures of faces, tools or cars.
Researchers are also studying the psychology of human way-finding, the often illogical reasons why people decide to take Route A to get to their destination, rather than Routes B or C.
''A lot of operations research and other math models have assumed that people want to take the shortest path to where they are going, and that the particular route they choose, and the sequence of turns they make, will be tied in with the principle of minimizing time and distance,'' said Dr. Reginald Golledge, a professor of geography at the University of California at Santa Barbara. ''Well, an increasing amount of research shows that people don't act like that.''
Instead, people make their way-finding choices based on what ''feels'' right. For example, people like to head off in the direction of their destination. If their endpoint is east, they hate to start by going west, even when an initial jog westward may deliver them to a more efficient route.
Another preferred strategy is called ''longest leg first.'' When conceptualizing a route, Dr. Golledge said, ''people try to start off going the longest and straightest distance possible before making the first turn.''
Choices can also be idiosyncratic. Many drivers seek out roads with the fewest stop signs and traffic lights, no matter how circuitous the route. Drivers like me will always take the most familiar course, and if that road is closed off, will go home and call a taxi.
Nobody knows yet why people make the navigational choices they do. Nor do they know why some people never get lost, while others always need to get found.
One creature that never goes astray is the bobolink, a member of the blackbird family that carries out the longest migratory journey of any songbird in the world. Bobolinks breed as far north as upper New York State and Canada, and then migrate as far south as the southern pampas of Argentina.
''These birds travel 10,000 miles a year,'' said Dr. Robert C. Beason, a professor of biology at the State University of New York in Geneseo. ''But I catch banded birds year after year in the same location.''
Equally impressive is the honeybee, which navigates chiefly and almost unerringly by the sun. It does this by its detailed grasp of the so-called solar ephemeris, the geographic position of sun as a function of time of day. After just a few hours of flying around in the sunshine, a bee has mastered the local solar arc. It then maps that geographic information onto its surroundings, a transfer that allows it to find its way around even on a cloudy day, and to tell its comrades, by waggling and dancing, how to locate a sweet patch of flowers.
Yet good as the great migrators may be, it turns out that they are not very different from people. ''The most interesting thing about animal navigation is that it appears to be done in ways similar to the principles taught in marine navigation classes,'' said Randy Gallistel, a professor of psychology at the University of California at Los Angeles.
There are two fundamental ways of navigating, he explained. One is called path integration, which most people know of as dead reckoning, a corruption of the term ''ded. reckoning,'' for deduced reckoning. In this method, you estimate your direction and speed, and use that to calculate how far you have gone. ''If you keep a scrupulous account of what direction you're going in, you can keep adding it up as you go, so you're reckoning, or calculating, your position in this way,'' Dr. Gallistel said. ''This method of of navigating doesn't require anything out there you recognize, which is why you can use it in the open ocean.''
The other method of navigation is piloting, relying on landmarks or maps of known objects to locate yourself in space.
How a given traveler reckons its course, or which landmarks it pilots by, varies from species to species and moment to moment. Animals can navigate by the position of the sun and stars, by the polarization of light, by smell, by echo-location. Some can use the earth's magnetic fields to direct them, and others attend to currents in the air or water. Researchers have learned that the key to migrational brilliance is versatility, the power to exploit different environmental cues depending on which is the richest in directional information at any given moment.
Homing pigeons, for example, have the capacity to detect the earth's magnetic field and respond to it, through specialized receptors in the front of their brains, between their eyes and nasal organs. But in regions that are magnetically flat, Dr. Beason said, the pigeons pay greater heed to the sun, or to chemical cues, to get home.
''It's very hard to disrupt them,'' Dr. Gallistel said. ''Even if you put Ping-Pong balls over their eyes, they get home again.'' Some evidence suggests that pigeons can be disrupted on their course by extreme magnetic storms, disturbances in the atmosphere caused by solar flares.
Hobbyists race homing pigeons across North America, Dr. Beason said, and those years when there is a poor return rate of the birds are correlated with strong magnetic storms. Alternatively, the birds may have found a more appealing park or gutter en route. ''The pigeons you see on the street,'' Dr. Beason said, ''are homing pigeons that didn't make it back home.''
But not all animals are so savvy. Rodents, for example, can be surprisingly limited in their ability to way-find. Through a famous series of experiments, Dr. Gallistel and his colleagues discovered that rodents, when introduced into a box and presented with a food reward in one corner, use the shape of the box, and only the shape, to relocate the cache later. If the wall near the food is painted a different color than the other three, or similar visual cues are provided, the rodent ignores them and depends on geometry alone.
Recently, Dr. Elizabeth Spelke, a professor of cognitive science at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology in Cambridge, and her colleague Dr. Linda Hermer-Vasquez, discovered that toddlers are like rats: they, too, use the shape of the environment to find their way and disregard distinctive surface features. The researchers studied children 18 months to 2 years old, placing them in a rectangular room with three white walls and one a striking shade of blue or red. They showed the toddlers a toy hidden in one corner, near the colorful wall. Covering the children's eyes and slowly turning them around a couple of times to disorient them, the researchers then told the toddlers to look for the toy. The toddlers ignored the brightness of the wall where the toy was hidden, and used their sense of the room's shape in their searching strategies.
By the time children reach the age of 5 or 6, though, Dr. Spelke said, they are quite capable of using color and other landmarks to find their way. ''This is also the time when we see them start to use spatial language to describe the environment, saying things like 'It's near the blue wall,' or, 'It's on the left.' ''
Dr. Spelke proposes that people's ability to use landmarks in way-finding is intimately correlated with language skills. She and Dr. Hermer-Vasquez experimented with adults, asking them to relocate an object that had been hidden in a room, all the while subjecting the adults to verbal interference tasks known to occupy the brain's language processor. ''We turned the adults back into toddlers,'' Dr. Spelke said. ''They continued to be sensitive to the shape of the environment but were no longer using visual landmarks to reorient themselves.''
With language skills, we have become superlative way-finders of another sort, able to draw maps and atlases, lay out cities with a grid pattern and numbered buildings, design subway lines, invent chronometers and radar, and, most important, stop and ask for directions.
