In Quest to Cure Rare Diseases, Some Get Left Out

If there was a defining moment, a single event that foretold the sadness to come, Eric Godek's parents do not mention it. Looking back, they say only that he was 4 months old when they began to notice things that worried them. He seemed to have lost the ability to lift his head and reach for his toys, and he had begun to choke on feedings.
At first, their pediatrician in Peoria reassured them that Eric, a bright, lively baby with huge brown eyes, seemed healthy. Jessica and David Godek, new parents in their 20's, were eager to believe him.
''But I think in my heart I knew something was wrong,'' Mrs. Godek said.
On Aug. 10, just after Eric turned 5 months old, the Godeks learned that he was suffering from a rare muscle disorder, Pompe disease, and that he had just two or three months left to live.
Desperate to save him, they found one speck of hope: researchers at Duke University Medical Center in Durham, N.C., were testing a highly promising experimental treatment in which infants like Eric were given an essential enzyme that they lacked. The Godeks contacted the university, and were encouraged to send Eric's medical records. He had exactly the form of the disease being studied.
But soon after the hope was offered, it was taken away. They were told that although the research team wanted to treat their son, it would not be possible, because the study was designed to include only three babies, and the company sponsoring the research, Synpac Inc., of the nearby Research Triangle Park, had provided enough medicine for only three. There was not enough for a fourth baby, even though the first three had been promised a lifetime supply if the drug worked. And Eric Godek would have been the fourth.
Pompe (pronounced pom-PAY) is an ''orphan'' disease, one of about 5,000 disorders so uncommon that drug companies used to ignore them, assuming there would be too few customers to make it pay to develop treatments. Many of the disorders are severe or fatal, and in 1983, hoping to encourage research, the government began offering tax credits, research grants and other incentives to companies working to treat rare diseases.
The incentives, provided under the Orphan Drug Act, worked. In the decade before it was passed, fewer than 10 orphan drugs came to market; since the act, 193 have been approved, nearly half of them in the last five years. In large part because of the government incentives, several so-called orphan drugs now make their manufacturers more than $1 billion a year.
''The act has been one of the most successful laws ever passed by Congress,'' said Dr. Marlene Haffner, director of the office of orphan products development at the Food and Drug Administration. ''It's just been gangbusters.''
But in the tide of investment capital, start-up companies, new drug applications, competition for marketing rights and confidential business deals, it is possible for a child to be lost. Companies competing to be first to market an orphan drug need to move quickly, and they have no more incentive than any other drug company to spend the time or money to enlarge a study. Mr. and Mrs. Godek found that a drug development strategy meant to benefit patients like their son had no provision to help him in a crisis. It rewarded manufacturers for creating new drugs, but not for making experimental treatments available to sick people with no other options.
Eric Godek died on Sept. 28, and his parents were left with piercing questions about whether his death might have been avoided.
A Big-Money Industry Built on Exclusivity
About 20 million Americans have orphan diseases: rare disorders, each one affecting fewer than 200,000 people. They include familiar illnesses like sickle cell anemia and cystic fibrosis, but also many others like Pompe disease that few have heard of.
Most of the work on orphan drugs is done by small-  to medium-sized biotechnology companies created to develop new products. Some have been started by researchers who struck out on their own, backed by investors, to commercialize discoveries made in university laboratories.
Under the Orphan Drug Act, these companies can get waivers of F.D.A. filing fees, worth $300,000 per drug, in addition to grants and tax credits. Especially important, a company that is first to receive F.D.A. approval for a particular orphan drug also gets exclusive marketing rights to it for seven years. Companies then set their own prices; even though money from taxpayers may have supported the development of an orphan drug, the F.D.A. does not regulate the pricing of the final products.
Many orphan drugs cannot be patented, Dr. Haffner said, either because they are natural substances or because they are old products whose original patents have run out by the time a new use is found for them. ''That's why exclusivity has been so important,'' she said. ''It is stronger than a patent, because F.D.A. will monitor it.'' In the case of new drugs that can be patented, the exclusive rights can come into effect before a patent does.
Abbey Meyers, president of the National Organization for Rare Disorders, in New Fairfield, Conn., said, ''The biotechnology industry was built on the Orphan Drug Act. These companies realize that if they make drugs for diabetes and high blood pressure, they can take a tiny piece of a big market with a lot of competition. But if they go into a rare disease, there's no competition. They can charge anything they want.''
As a result, orphan drugs are among the biotechnology industry's biggest moneymakers. One, a replacement enzyme, like the treatment being studied for Pompe disease, costs $170,000 to $340,000 a year per patient.
Fingers Are Pointed As a Child Dies
Pompe disease, also known as acid maltase deficiency, is caused by a deficiency in an enzyme called acid alpha glucosidase. Normally, the enzyme helps the body break down glycogen, a complex carbohydrate that is converted to glucose for energy. Without the enzyme, glycogen builds up in the heart and other muscles, causing extensive damage.
The disorder is caused by a genetic defect inherited from both parents, and most, like the Godeks, have no idea they are carriers of a lethal gene until they find they have given birth to a seriously ill child.
There are several forms of Pompe disease, varying in severity, and researchers estimate that there are 3,000 to 6,000 cases at any given time in the United States. The type that Eric Godek had is rapidly fatal, because it damages the heart and the muscles needed for breathing. But the brain is spared, and babies remain as bright and aware as ever while they weaken and become immobile.
In May, Duke University Medical Center announced that it would begin a clinical trial to test an experimental treatment in three babies with the most severe form of Pompe disease. The treatment, injections of the missing enzyme, had been developed by Dr. Yuan-Tsong Chen, a professor of pediatrics and genetics and chief of medical genetics. Babies in the study would live at the hospital with a parent for three months.
The trial was paid for by Synpac Inc., the drug development company in Research Triangle Park, with a parent company in Britain and owners in Taiwan. The university had licensed Dr. Chen's technology to Synpac. A spokesman for Synpac said it had invested millions in the research, and had contracted the actual manufacturing to still another company, which the spokesman declined to name.
Duke and Synpac have competition: a Dutch company, Pharming Group N.V., is also testing a replacement enzyme in the Netherlands, and hoping for F.D.A. approval. Its partner in the research is Genzyme, of Cambridge, Mass.
Much is at stake: whichever company can be the first to prove its treatment works and get F.D.A. approval will also win the seven years of exclusive marketing rights.
The Godeks knew there was no guarantee that the treatment would work. But they also knew that the first infant in the Duke study was still alive, past the time when the disease would normally have taken his life. To them, the study was Eric's only chance. Two babies had already been chosen, but they were told that Eric might qualify for the third spot. Another child, though, was also being evaluated.
They were devastated to learn that Eric would not be part of the study after all. The other baby had qualified first. Even though Eric had the rapidly fatal form of Pompe disease being studied, even though he was the only additional qualified applicant, the Godeks were told that there was not enough medicine or enough staff to take care of him.
To the Godeks, that defied logic. If enough enzyme could be made to treat three children for life, how could it not be possible to make enough to keep a fourth alive? ''I think they're in competition to get the patent and they don't want to let anything slow them down,'' Mrs. Godek said, shortly before her son died.  ''The drug company and the investors are making a business decision.''
In telephone interviews before Eric's death, Dr. Chen and an official at Synpac declined to address those questions. They would not explain how long it took to produce the enzyme, or say whether enough could be made in time to treat him. Initially, Dr. Chen said Synpac had declared that the baby could not be treated, but Synpac officials said Dr. Chen had decided. Finally, both Synpac and Dr. Chen blamed a third party, the company manufacturing the drug, which they declined to name.
But Dr. Chen said that if the drug were available, he would want to treat Eric. ''Other than the parents, I am probably the one most desperate to help these babies.''
By late September, the Godek family had appealed to Synpac, the orphan drug office at the F.D.A. and even their United States senator, Richard J. Durbin, an Illinois Democrat, who called Synpac on their behalf, to no avail.
Dr. Haffner said the orphan drug office was also powerless to help. The F.D.A. can let patients have unapproved drugs for ''compassionate use,'' she said, but cannot help if the drug is not available. If the problem had been money, she said, Synpac could have asked the F.D.A. for a grant.
Ms. Meyers, of the rare disease organization, said: ''Biotechnology companies, being small and not as wealthy, don't have the money to invest in manufacturing a huge amount of a drug before they know whether the F.D.A. is going to approve it or not. If it costs $50 million to make it and the F.D.A. doesn't approve it, they'll go bankrupt. They hold back until they get approval.''
She said that in several cases, even when new orphan drugs were approved and marketed, companies could not meet the demand for them. For example, she said, new treatments for multiple sclerosis and Lou Gehrig's disease were initially in such short supply that patients had to enter their names into lotteries to obtain the drugs.
''American patients are not used to rationing,'' she said. ''The rest of the world is. I think people in the United States are going to have to get used to it. It's going to happen more and more.''
Time ran out on the morning of Sept. 28 when, after a night of struggling to breathe, Eric Godek died at a hospital in Peoria.
Later that day, Mr. Godek said that he and his wife would always wonder whether their son's death might have been avoided. ''I'm trying not to be bitter,'' Mrs. Godek said. ''But something has to be done so this doesn't happen again and again and again.''
