Boom in Gene Testing Raises Questions on Sharing Results

As genetic testing becomes increasingly common, those who choose to learn their genetic risks, and the health professionals who treat them, are facing difficult decisions about how -- and whether -- to share the results with family members who share their genes.
And the new genetic information is creating new kinds of rifts, when one family member finds out what another family member does not want to know, or when family members react differently to the same knowledge.
''One woman who'd had ovarian cancer was tested for the breast cancer gene mutations mostly for the sake of her two adult daughters,'' said Katherine Schneider, senior genetics counselor at the Dana Farber Cancer Institute in Boston. ''But when she told them she had it, they were so devastated that they didn't talk with her for two years. They didn't want to know.
''I tell that story a lot. There's nothing easy about any of this. But before testing, it's important to talk not only about what the information will mean for you, but what it might mean to your sisters, your children, your cousins.''
Genetic tests are now commonplace, what with prenatal tests diagnosing hundreds of syndromes, midlife tests for mutations linked to breast and ovarian cancer, and -- with the human genome newly mapped -- more and more familial disorders.
The scientific advances have created debate about public policy on genetic discrimination. But the private effects on family dynamics are just as complex, as patients and health professionals adjust to thinking about family not just as flesh and blood, but flesh and blood and genes.
Usually, patients are happy to share health information with family members for whom it may be important, often asking the doctor or genetic counselor for a written explanation to pass along.
But when patients want to keep the information to themselves, health professionals may encounter situations that mix social problem and soap opera, and be  ethically and legally pulled into uncharted waters.
A young man in Washington State called his genetics counselor to confess a guilty conscience: Several months earlier, he told her, he had made a sperm donation. And while he knew his test results had shown that he had an inheritable syndrome that causes heart trouble and, often, early death, he did not mention it to the sperm bank. Troubled, the counselor called the sperm bank and found that there had, indeed, been successful pregnancies with the man's sperm. She offered to counsel those families but does not know whether the sperm bank even passed on the information.
In a New York family with three adult daughters, the two married daughters know that their mother, who had breast cancer as a young woman, has been tested and found to carry a gene mutation associated with a high risk of breast and ovarian cancer. The mother has forbidden them to tell their unmarried sister, who has always felt herself to be the least attractive, for fear that it might make her less marriageable. They have obeyed, but want the family doctor  to make sure she has frequent mammograms and screenings.
Two sisters who know their mother had genetic testing before she died of ovarian cancer want to find out her test results. But the Pennsylvania medical center that did the testing will not release the results to the young women without the consent of their stepfather, who has a dismal relationship with them. The sisters could, of course, have had their own genetic tests, but they had hoped by learning more about their family's history to avoid the process. The center's ethics committee is now revising its consent forms to require all patients tested to specify which family members should have access to the results after their death.
One California genetics counselor tells of her confusion when a couple who had a child with cystic fibrosis came to discuss their risks for future pregnancies, and in providing a family history, the wife mentioned that her estranged half-sister had a baby who died from a serious congenital defect. It was nothing genetic, she assured the counselor. But the counselor knew otherwise: The sister had been an earlier client.
''It just rang a bell in my head,'' the counselor said. ''I remembered the name, and I remembered telling her it was genetic, and she should tell her relatives. I didn't know what to do. But I didn't want to breach confidentiality for either one of them.''
Eventually, she called the previous client on the pretext of a routine records check. ''I played dumb, saying I just happened to have her file on my desk,'' the counselor said, ''and I'd noticed we'd talked about telling her family the results, and I was just following up for the records, wondering if that conversation had taken place, and she said, why, no, it hadn't.
''So I reminded her why it was important. And a few days later, I had a call from the current client, who said the funniest thing had happened, she'd had a call from her half-sister, and there was a genetic problem.''
Often, the decision to pass on information is a delicate one, depending not only on such factors as the relatives' closeness, ages and emotional health, but also the nature of the disease and the severity of the risk.  Where there is no treatment, or the risk is small, the case for sharing painful knowledge becomes less compelling. And the need to share information may be temporary, experts say, as the era approaches when complete genetic profiles become a routine part of individual health records. Meanwhile, the cost of testing even a single gene can run from several hundred to several thousand dollars.
Still, Josephine Wagner Costalas, a genetic counselor at Fox Chase Cancer Center in Philadelphia, has an unspoken worry whenever she counsels a patient who has tested positive for the breast cancer gene mutations.
''My worst nightmare is the scenario where I might have a patient who tests positive and doesn't tell her relatives,'' Ms. Costalas said, ''and a few years later her sister will discover she has metastatic cancer, with a bad prognosis, and she'll find out that there was this information showing she was at risk. And maybe she'll sue me, saying I should have picked up the phone and told her, 'Your sister's positive, you should get tested.' This is all so new, and there are no clear guidelines, so I worry.''
Still, Ms. Costalas does not pressure her patients to share their results. ''If people aren't sure about sharing the information, I ask them to think about what it would be like if the situation were reversed,'' she said. ''Would they want to know? But I do believe patients need to decide for themselves what they want to do.''
And when several family members come in together, there are other issues. ''What if they have different results?'' Ms. Costalas said. ''Who do you tell first? What if they have different reactions?''
Andrea Shumsky, whom Ms. Costalas counseled recently, never had any doubt about sharing her results. There has been a lot of cancer in Ms. Shumsky's family: Her father had early-onset colon cancer, his sister had breast cancer, three of his other siblings had colon cancer, and her grandfather had melanoma. Ms. Shumsky herself learned she had melanoma last year, on her 40th birthday, and the breast cancer gene mutations she was being tested for carry a higher risk of melanoma.
She listened as Ms. Costalas told her that the test was negative, that there was no sign that the melanoma was genetic, but that it might be worth pursuing further genetic testing for colon cancer. Then Ms. Costalas asked about Ms. Shumsky's plans to share her results.
''My sister knows I'm here, and I'm going to tell her the results as soon as I get home,'' Ms. Shumsky said. ''And I'm going to tell her about the colon cancer. After walking around with a mole for years, and then finding out it was melanoma, I want everyone in my family to watch out for cancer.
''After I got my diagnosis, I called her doctor myself, and told him she needed melanoma screening. I know it's butting into her life, but if she never talks to me again, and I save her life, it's worth the risk.''
Two years ago, the American Society of Human Genetics adopted a position recognizing the conflict between the health professions' duty to maintain confidentiality and the duty to warn about serious health risks. Health professionals should tell patients about potential genetic risks to their relatives, the statement said, and in some cases, they may be allowed to breach confidentiality to warn relatives at risk if the harm is ''serious, imminent and likely'' and prevention or treatment is available.
But there is little consensus on where to draw those lines. Generally, genetic counselors are more concerned about confidentiality and not pressuring patients, while physicians specializing in genetics are more concerned about the duty to warn, according to research by Dorothy C. Wertz, senior scientist at the Shriver Center in Waltham, Mass. As a practical matter, though, most health professionals cannot warn relatives.
''In the end it's up to the patient, because in real life, we don't have relatives' names and phone numbers,'' said Helen Hixon, a genetic counselor in cardiology at Cedars Sinai hospital in Los Angeles. ''We do tell people pretty strongly that they  should warn their relatives, that they may have a legal duty to do so.''
Bioethics lawyers say that while patients may have some moral obligation, they have no legal duty to warn relatives. There have been at least two legal rulings, one in a 1995 Florida case and the other in a 1996 New Jersey case, giving conflicting signals on whether doctors can be held liable for not warning a patient's relatives about their risks of a hereditary form of cancer.
Although the tensions involving  family disclosure of genetic risks are not new, the issue has become more complicated as genetic tests proliferate, and it becomes possible to identify a person's predisposition to common diseases.
''It used to be that most of these issues came up around rare disorders, where there was a recessive gene that became a problem only when it met up with another carrier,'' said Vivian Weinblatt, president elect of the National Society of Genetic Counselors. ''Now we're talking about areas where it's all gray, where it's a gene that predisposes you to some disease you might get anyway in late middle age.''
The breast cancer gene mutations are the latest case in point and the fastest growing area of testing. While most cases of breast and ovarian cancer are not hereditary, women with specific mutations in the BRCA 1 or BRCA 2 genes have a lifetime risk of breast or ovarian cancer over 50 percent, odds so high that many women who test positive choose to have their breasts and ovaries removed.
''My mother died of breast cancer when I was 15, and my older sister got it when she was 41,'' said a 43-year old New York woman who had the preventive surgery but told only three people. ''I knew as soon as I tested positive that I would do anything I could to get my odds down. But it's been awkward with my sister, who's against prophylactic surgery. I think she's crazy, she thinks I'm crazy and we don't talk about it anymore. Instead of it being a shared family thing, it's made us less close.''
In some families, particularly Ashkenazi Jewish families, which are more likely to carry the mutations, the testing is a pressure point.
''In one of our early research families, with a serious history of cancer, there was a push from the family matriarch that anyone found to have the mutation should get a mastectomy,'' said Jill Stopfer at the University of Pennsylvania Cancer Center. ''The push was so strong that some of the younger women decided they wouldn't get tested, not because they couldn't handle the results, but because they were worried about the family pressure to have surgery.''
