SCIENTIST AT WORK: Joan Roughgarden; A Theorist With Personal Experience Of the Divide Between the Sexes

Speaking to a standing room only crowd at the annual meeting of the Ecological Society of America in Snowbird, Utah, Dr. Joan Roughgarden, one of the world's most influential theoretical ecologists, is methodically taking apart the way that biologists think about sex.
Providing details that make some titter and shift nervously in their seats, she is re-thinking orgasms and the architecture of female genitals, making arguments for the existence of more than two genders and presenting evidence for widespread homosexual copulation in the wild.
''What's coming out now is to the rest of the species what the Kinsey Report was to humans,'' she says later, discussing recent research.
Described as a visionary and iconoclast who consistently ignores disciplinary and conceptual boundaries, Dr. Roughgarden always draws a good crowd. But on this August day the room is packed, in part because this is not just more talk about science, but the outgrowth of a personal experience that two years ago riveted this entire community of scientists.
That was when Dr. Roughgarden crossed the most rigidly enforced boundary of all, the divide between the sexes. Born Jonathan Roughgarden, she became Joan in the spring of 1998 -- a profound transformation that has led her not only onto new paths in science but into San Francisco politics as well.
''People are wrapping their minds around this,'' said Dr. Roughgarden of re-meeting colleagues. ''They don't quite know what to say.''
Whatever they may have been thinking about Dr. Roughgarden herself, the ecologists at the meeting seemed to welcome the new work, though it remains to be seen whether her radically different views of sex and mating will take hold, or be dismissed.
''This is the usual sort of mold-breaking creativity that she brings to a problem, not just this problem,'' said Dr. Steve Pacala, an ecologist at Princeton.  ''Just because she broke her own mold it's particularly applicable here, but the kind of thing she always does with a problem is think about it afresh.''
For those who knew Dr. Jonathan Roughgarden well, and the many more who knew him only through his prolific production of scientific papers and books, it came as a much-discussed surprise when this Stanford professor, then 52, announced on his Web site that he was a transsexual, posting pictures of himself as Joan.
''It became clear to me that I wasn't ever going to figure out how to do the guy thing,'' Dr. Roughgarden said. She believes that gender is a matter of cognition, an instinctive ability and desire to learn a certain way of being, she said. ''Imagine as a woman if you'd set out to be a man, to learn how to live as a man. Could you do it? I couldn't. It's like asking a fish to fly.''
She said the light dawned on her one day as she sat in a department faculty meeting. ''There were all these guys around this table, staking out their territories and going at one another,'' she said. ''After a while I said, you know, this is not a battle you want to win. You don't want to be like them.''
But as Jonathan, Dr. Roughgarden, who in her own mind has always identified herself as female, was universally regarded as the quintessential macho academic: aggressive, abrasive and competitive.
''Aggressiveness is the easiest male trait to emulate,'' she explained in a recent interview at her apartment in San Francisco, where she has taken the unusual step for a high-powered academic of running for a public office. ''It's easy to duplicate.''
Such behavior, along with the talent to back it up, can play well in the male-dominated world of theoretical ecology, in which scientists study ecology using mathematical models, and in which Jonathan Roughgarden was at the top of his game.
''I don't think there are a lot of people who have been so influential or sweeping in their approach,'' said Dr. Ted Case, a theoretical ecologist at University of California at San Diego.
The transformation to Joan, Dr. Case said, appears not to have diminished Dr. Roughgarden's status in the field. Her gift, he said, is ''to look at the natural world and convert it to math.'' He added, ''I've looked forward to a new paper by Joan or Jon the way the world looks forward to the next Harry Potter book.''
Known for her itinerant interests, Dr. Roughgarden has boiled down into mathematical expression complex ecological phenomena, including what drives some species to produce many offspring and others to produce just a few, and how predators decide which prey to chase and which to let scramble away.
And, unlike most theoreticians, Dr. Roughgarden has gotten her hands dirty doing field studies, looking, for example, at competition between lizards on the Caribbean islands. Even now, in addition to her work on sex and gender, she continues work on very different projects, including developing a theory on the relationship between economics and ecology.
In many ways, Dr. Roughgarden's transition to life as a woman mirrors that of other transsexuals. Tall, slender and somewhat androgynous looking, she has spent two years preoccupied with her physical appearance as she made the transition from one gender to another. Over the same period, she also settled into a softer, more traditionally feminine demeanor.
Moderating a discussion at the meetings in Snowbird, she operated as colleagues said Jonathan never would have: seeking out consensus, affirming others' opinions, welcoming dialogue.
Other scientists universally describe Joan as friendlier, more nurturing and significantly happier-seeming than Jon.
''I've seen Joan smile more in two years than I saw Jon smile in the last 20,'' said Dr. Paul Ehrlich, an ecologist and longtime colleague of Dr. Roughgarden's at Stanford.
Dr. Roughgarden insists she is in many ways entirely unchanged. She acknowledges, however, that life as a woman is quite different.
''At first I was amused,'' Dr. Roughgarden said, describing how she is now much more frequently interrupted, ignored and condescended to by men, particularly those who did not know her as Jonathan. ''I thought, if women are discriminated against, then I'm darn well going to be discriminated against the same way. Well, the thrill of that's worn off, I can tell you.''
Dr. Roughgarden's transformation is leading toward what she hopes will be a change in how biologists think about gender, courtship and reproduction.
In the world view of nearly all biologists, there are males and there are females and they mate only with one another. Dr. Roughgarden likewise had not questioned these most basic of premises. But that began to change when, seeking to understand what science could tell her about herself as a transsexual, she began reviewing the literature. She presents her results in ''Evolution's Rainbow,'' a book to be published by Princeton University Press.
What she found, she said, was that biologists have been unsuccessfully trying to cram the immense variation in nature -- the rainbows, as she calls them, both in gender and mating -- into overly simple, outdated categories.
''There are two sexes,'' she said, meaning females that produce large reproductive cells like eggs and males that produce small ones, like sperm. ''But how you package those sexes is all over the waterfront.''
Hermaphrodites, for example, which can produce both eggs and sperm, do not fit the standard male or female definitions, yet they are widespread in nature. In some species, male-female lines are blurred where sexual identities are flexible.
In fish known as wrasses, for example, some large females change into males later in life and have harems of females, while small males remain male for life, mating with females under the large males' control. Some females remain female for life.
Curiously, Dr. Roughgarden noted, biologists consider females that turn into large males to be the standard males while the life-long males are considered ''sneakers'' and are described as having an alternative mating strategy.
In Dr. Roughgarden's framework, rather than designate any type as the normal or alternative, scientists would recognize the fundamental difference between these three differently sexed, shaped, sized and behaving fish and designate them as different genders.
Dr. Roughgarden said scientists had also been shockingly blind to same-sex mating.
''There are 303 published examples of species with same-sex courtship,'' she said of behaviors typically discounted as anomalies. ''We know examples are suppressed. No one wants to say the organism they work on is gay.''
Rather than view mating through the conventional lens of sexual selection, in which competing males vie for choosy females and in which same-sex courtship becomes invisible, she suggests biologists think instead in terms of the evolution of courtship and mating in general -- between males, between females as well as between females and males. In fact, Dr. Roughgarden argues that same-sex copulation is so widespread that scientists must test the idea that, rather than being a mistake, homosexual behaviors may have some advantages in an evolutionary sense.
Just as she hopes the work of gay and transsexual scientists will improve the scientific understanding of sex and mating, Dr. Roughgarden said she believed a wide diversity of perspectives would lead to better governance. For that reason, she is running for the half-time, city council-like position of district supervisor for District 6, which includes some of the poorest parts of San Francisco.
''I got tired of people saying we need to convince the politicians,'' she said, referring to the common lament of scientists who feel their perspective is lost or misunderstood by politicians and the public. ''Instead of trying to convince them, let's just do it.''
Walking through the district with Dr. Roughgarden, one sees the beginnings of what is promised to be a upscale new development, called Mission Bay, which includes a new University of California campus. It sits alongside neighborhoods where  homeless people sleep in doorways and others pick through the trash.
''Some ecological thinking could really help,'' said Dr. Roughgarden, who has promised to use her expertise in the analyses of complex systems to rethink the growth of District 6. She has already crunched the numbers.
''The displacement of people will be enormous,'' she said.''And they're not going to go quietly.''
To create more of a sense of community between the new campus and the rest of the district, Dr. Roughgarden is proposing that two large piers extending into the bay near the university be developed as Diversity Plaza, home to a statue celebrating diversity. ''I imagine it as the West Coast's equivalent to the Statue of Liberty,'' she said.
Hank Wilson, a longtime community activist and a friendly competitor running for the same office, said Dr. Roughgarden, a political novice, and Diversity Plaza had captured people's imagination. ''Joan is on people's radar screen,'' he said.
Always mathematically minded, Dr. Roughgarden notes that with 17 candidates vying for the position and no incumbent, everyone theoretically has a chance. Still, considered a dark horse, she remains philosophical about where she has come from and where she is going.
''One thing I've learned is that almost all professional women have had a very nonlinear path to get where they are,'' said Dr. Roughgarden, who said she intended to pursue her science whatever the outcome on Nov. 7. ''It's taken me a while to get here, but we've all got a story.''
