A Pill to Extend Life? Don't Dismiss the Notion Too Quickly

Offering a sharp insight into the nature of aging, biologists report today that they have shown precisely why a calorically restricted diet prolongs life span, at least in a lower organism. The finding, should it prove true of people too, would open the possibility of developing drugs to mimic the effects and gain the remarkable benefits of the draconian low-calorie diet.
Laboratory rats and mice live up to 40 percent longer than usual when fed a diet that has at least 30 percent fewer calories than they would usually eat though otherwise contains all necessary vitamins and nutrients. The animals are free of age-related disease and appear healthy in every respect except that they are generally less fertile.
Studies with rhesus monkeys, which usually live around 25 years, have not been in progress for long enough to say if caloric restriction is likely to benefit primates like monkeys and people, though initial signs are positive.
Even if caloric restriction does prove to prolong human life, very few people could adhere to such a meager diet. Other means, ideally a simple pill, might capture the benefits. But drugs require a target to act on, and the mechanism by which caloric restriction affects life span has long been a mystery.
The issue now seems to have been settled at least in yeast, a widely studied laboratory organism whose metabolism is similar to that of animals in many fundamental ways.
Dr. Leonard Guarente and colleagues at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology report in today's issue of Science that caloric restriction extends life span in yeast because it interacts with a gene that controls the activity of DNA, the genetic material.
The gene is known as SIR2, for silent information regulator No. 2, and its product, the SIR2 protein, silences genes by making the material that clads the DNA wrap more tightly, thus denying a cell access to the underlying genes.
The SIR2 gene has a direct effect on the yeast cell's longevity; Dr. Guarente previously found that yeast cells in which the gene had been disrupted lived shorter lives than usual, while those given an extra copy of SIR2 lived longer.
Gene silencing is probably of great importance to the integrity of a cell because to have the wrong genes activated could derange a cell's function. Dr. Guarente believes that inefficient silencing in cells could explain many of the infirmities of age.
He and colleagues have now found that caloric restriction appears to work through the SIR2 gene pathway. Yeast cells grown with very little of their food, sugar in the form of glucose, lived longer than normal, but not if their SIR2 gene was disrupted.
The reason seems to be that both the cell's glucose metabolism system, and the protein made by the SIR2 gene, compete for the same chemical, a substance known as NAD. The SIR2 protein cannot perform its silencing duties unless it has NAD to help it, but when the cell is busily converting glucose to energy, there is less NAD available for the SIR2 protein.
Dr. Guarente's next project is to see if his findings in yeast are also true of higher organisms. Both mice and people have their own versions of the SIR2 gene, and the protein requires NAD to function.
The mechanism makes evolutionary sense, Dr. Guarente said, because when food is scarce an organism's best strategy is to postpone reproduction and wait until conditions improve. So a gene like SIR2 that linked greater longevity to lower calorie intake would be highly favored by the forces of natural selection.
Dr. Tomas A. Prolla, a geneticist who studies aging at the University of Wisconsin, said Dr. Guarente's report was the first to link the life extension effects of caloric restriction to a single gene.
''If the find can be translated to animals, it will be very important,'' Dr. Prolla said, because it would provide ''a starting point in the design of drugs which would have a broad effect on human health, including cancer.''
The 40 percent life extension seen under caloric restriction could be just a hint of what would be possible once the underlying mechanism is understood. ''I don't think a 30-40 percent range should be considered as some kind of maximum,'' Dr. Prolla said.
Dr. George S. Roth of the National Institute of Aging, who has been conducting a calorie restriction study on rhesus monkeys since 1987, said there had been fewer deaths so far among the dieting monkeys, which receive 30 percent fewer calories, than among a comparison group that feeds normally.
The mortality difference is not yet statistically significant, Dr. Roth said, but the restricted monkeys have already developed metabolic patterns suggesting they will prove more resistant to diabetes and heart disease.
There is an interesting difference of opinion on the subject of aging between evolutionary biologists, who believe for strong theoretical reasons that aging must be influenced by many different genes, and molecular biologists who have found they can extend the life of laboratory organisms by altering single genes.
Reflecting this difference, Dr. Michael Rose, an evolutionary biologist at the University of California at Irvine, said that the work with yeast was ''really nice and elegant'' but that Dr. Guarente was mistaken in arguing that gene silencing or any other single mechanism of aging was likely to be universal.
Dr. Guarente acknowledged that many genes might be involved in aging. But there is likely to be a single major genetic pathway, he said, in the form of a mechanism to slow aging in response to food scarcity, because any such mechanism would be heavily favored by the forces of natural selection.
