In Mandrill Society, Life is a Girl Thing

It was a moment when the sublime met the ridiculous, Jane Goodall by way of the Marx Brothers.
Kate Abernethy and her fellow primatologists were driving through the Lope Reserve of Gabon, in Central Africa, a gorgeous checkerboard mosaic of open savanna grassland and dense, galleried tropical rainforest. Suddenly they spied a group of mandrills crossing the road just a few yards in front of them, the distinctively colorful primates loping along in snappy single file.
In a flash, the scientists realized that the great monkey god had smiled on them, and that the military procession gave them a chance to get an accurate count of a mandrill group, something that, although the baboon-like creatures have been known about and admired for centuries, nobody had ever managed to do. Yanking out a hand-held video camera, the researchers started shooting, literally, from the hip. As the large, raucous battalion passed in front of her, Dr. Abernethy, of the International Center for Medical Research in Gabon, tried to quickly describe on the videotape the sex of each individual, and whether it was adult or juvenile.
''Female, female, female,'' she muttered, keeping her voice low so as not to frighten the monkeys. ''Juvenile, female, female, big male, big male, female.''
The mandrills kept crossing.
''Female, female, female, big male, female, female . . .''
Remember the classic scene in ''Night at the Opera,'' when people keep piling into Groucho's room, and just when you think it's stuffed beyond capacity, another guest pushes through the door?
''Female, female, female, juvenile, big male, female . . .''
Finally, Dr. Abernethy's immortal utterance (as heard on the video, which can be seen at the new Congo exhibit at the Bronx Zoo): ''Oh, forget it!'' And still the mandrills kept on coming . . .
''It was one of the most exciting experiences I'd ever had with primates in the wild,'' said Elizabeth Rogers of the University of Edinburgh in Scotland, who has worked at the Lope reserve periodically since 1984. ''The size of that group was really over the top, and there we were, filming it.''
The scientists' excitement only mounted when they replayed the tape and got the census they had sought: 604 mandrills, the largest aggregation of nonhuman primates ever observed. Nor was that particular mandrill group the most populous the scientists would encounter. In five years of rigorous study at Lope, the scientists have tallied hordes of 700, 800, up to 1,350.
Importantly, the primatologists have determined that the mandrill groups are extremely cohesive. Baboons are known to congregate while feeding in groups of maybe 150 individuals, but such crowds are fleeting, and will fission into their core social subunits of 30 or 40 animals once an area has been picked clean. By contrast, a group of 800 mandrills is a tightknit and stable society, traveling, foraging, breeding, playing, nuzzling and bickering together year after year. (The average mandrill lives for 15 years in the wild.)
It's like a movable version of Winesburg, Ohio -- with one big difference. In Sherwood Anderson's fictional community, as in nearly all primate societies, males are outstanding, if not always upstanding, members of the community.
But as Dr. Abernethy and her co-authors E. Jean Wickings and Lee J. T. White of the Wildlife Conservation Society describe in a new report that was presented last month at an ecology meeting in Orlando, and that will be published this year, the enduring mandrill social group consists almost entirely of females and their dependent offspring.
As astonished as the researchers were by the magnitude of a mandrill society, they have been equally surprised to discover that adult male mandrills interact with the group only when the females are in estrus, from June through early November. Once the breeding season is through, the males disappear, and spend the rest of the year in distinctly unsimian solitude. They don't even bother to form itinerant bachelor bands, as many male primates do. And should a male happen to spy a passing flock of females in the off-season, Curious George he ain't.
''He'll simply ignore them,'' Dr. Abernethy said in a telephone interview from Gabon, adding, ''Male mandrills don't invest in political relationships, as chimpanzees will. They don't establish long-term bonds with females. When they move into a group, at the beginning of a breeding season, they have to establish everything from scratch.''
Of the approximately 235 known species of primates, only the orangutan matches the male mandrill in its taste for the monkish life. The new findings overturn almost everything that has been said about the behavior and social life Mandrillus sphinx to date, and also call into question existing models of why primates form social groups.
''Everybody knew that mandrills were amazing animals, the type that gets featured by Disney,'' said Dr. John Oates, a zoologist and conservationist at Hunter College, referring to the mandrills' appearance in the animated blockbuster, ''The Lion King.''  But now mandrills turn out to be ''so amazing,'' he said, ''that all we can do is throw up our hands and speculate wildly about how they got to be the way they are.''
On a more somber note, the discoveries raise questions about the species' long-term prospects as a free-ranging creature. Conservationists are alarmed by how the recent rise in the so-called bush meat trade -- the hunting of wild animals in general and primates in particular -- might affect mandrill populations.
Because the new studies show that mandrills travel over unusually long distances in spectacularly large numbers, conservationists are concerned that the monkeys will be especially vulnerable to hunters using the ever-expanding network of logging roads to penetrate into forests that were once inaccessible to hunting. Some conservation organizations now rank the bush meat trade as the single greatest threat to primates and other wildlife, outstripping in severity even the familiar eco-villain, habitat loss.
''In case of species like mandrills, we have a real problem from hunting,'' said Dr. John G. Robinson, a vice president of Wildlife Conservation Society in the Bronx, which finances the mandrill project in Gabon. ''People like to eat them, they're very tasty, and they come in the right size. You can smoke them and transport them very easily. And because mandrills move in very large groups, they're pretty easy to find and to intercept, and to hunt in batches of 50, 100 or even more.''
At the moment, mandrills are classified as ''near-threatened,'' rather than ''endangered,'' but Dr. Robinson and his colleagues are taking steps while the numbers still offer hope for a creature that loves a crowd.
Among other things, the scientists are negotiating to expand the list of criteria that a logging company must meet if its wood is to be sanctioned as ''sustainable.'' By current practice, wood is certified as sustainable if a logging company cuts down only so many trees a year, avoids clear cutting and replants a certain percentage of what it takes.
The market for such environmentally correct wood is growing faster than you can say ''chain saw.'' Home Depot, the chain of home-improvement stores, has announced that it will buy sustainable wood whenever possible. Conservationists would like to append ''sensitivity to wildlife'' to the certification process, a stipulation that would impel logging companies to keep commercial hunters off their roads and away from the primate throngs.
That mandrills take group size to extremes is in keeping with the flamboyant creatures, which boast Guinness-type records in an array of categories. As Charles Darwin observed in 1871, the mandrill is the most vividly colored specimen in mammaldom, its lozenge-shaped muzzle of red and blue more like what you would expect on a bird than on the furred. The male gets gaudier still at sexual maturity, when his blue and red markings turn neon-bright and are further highlighted by the growth of dazzling white cheek ridges and a thick golden beard; and, just to be sure he is seen coming and going, his blue buttocks brighten as well.
At three feet in height and 90 pounds in weight, and with canine teeth the size of human thumbs, the adult male is the largest and most formidable of any monkey. Moreover, the sexual dimorphism, or size difference, between the male and the 25-pound female is among the most extreme in the primate order. Yet, though mandrills have been known about for centuries, prized as curiosities by potentates and long a favorite attraction in zoos, they have been little studied in the wilderness.
''They're extremely difficult to track when they're in the forest,'' Dr. Rogers explained.
Because mandrills look like Crayola versions of baboons, they were thought until recently to be close cousins of the Papio family, even members of it. Thus, mandrill society was usually described as baboonish in structure, composed of an alpha male and his dogged coterie of females. Some researchers suggested that the male mandrill's bright colors made it easier for him to lead ''his'' females through the forest.
Last year, however, a DNA study published in The Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences revealed that mandrills are neither baboons nor their next of kin. Instead, mandrills turn out to be most closely related to mangebays, short-legged tree-dwelling monkeys. Now the research at Lope is showing that, behaviorally, mandrills are a class unto themselves.
In addition to using videocameras to record troops as they traverse openings in the forest, the researchers have also managed to put radio collars on a number of adult mandrills, an approach that revealed the loneliness of the off-season male.
By collecting thousands of scat samples, the scientists have learned much about mandrill diet. It turns out that mandrills are finicky omnivores. They eat a little bit of a lot of things -- nuts, leaves, insects, fruit, grass, fungi, small vertebrates. They pick and choose and throw a lot away in disgust. A species of nut that pleases them in one spot may repel them in the next. They travel constantly as they forage, covering three or five miles a day, far more than most primates travel. Their home range is accordingly huge, 115 square miles or so, the largest such range known for any primate.
The researchers have also learned how violent a male's life can be.
''Of the six males that we collared, only one had all its canines intact,'' Dr. Abernethy said. ''All the rest had broken teeth, scars on the face, ripped nostrils up to the eye. One had such severe fresh puncture wounds that we could see the cartilage. We couldn't collar him, and I don't know if he survived after we let him go.'' The males get these wounds in violent battles with one another during mating season.
As it turns out, the males do not have much time to make their reproductive mark. They do not have harems, after all, and they cannot very well monopolize a female society numbering 800 strong.
Once females start coming into estrus, males from all around descend on the group. The males start grunting, panting, heaving noisily from the chest hour upon hour. They are so big, colorful, loud and impossible to ignore. They fight, yes, and they suffer from the lacerating canines of their competitors, but the primatologists propose that the males would suffer even greater damage if not for their dramatic appearance.
''Having seen the risks they take during actual fights,'' Dr. Abernethy said, ''I'd suspect that the incredible investment they make in color and auditory signaling is an attempt to minimize that risk.'' In other words, a male in his fully pigmented and baritone glory is trying to get the attention of at least some females as quickly as possible, before a rival suitor decides to go for his throat.
The researchers do not yet understand the why mandrill societies have evolved as they have. They do not know why so many females stick together, and they are just starting to do the studies to see whether all the females in a given troop are related.
Does large group size protect the female, and if so, from whom? Perhaps from predators, or perhaps from mandrill males. Whereas female baboons often display the wounds of the alpha males that seek to control them, female mandrills do not seem to be the recipients of mate abuse, despite the male's vastly superior size.
Can mandrills find safety in numbers should human hunters come to call? Don't bet a buffalo nickel on it.
