Tiniest of Particles Pokes Big Hole in Physics Theory

New observations of subatomic particles do not appear to fit into the standard theories explaining the matter and forces that shape the universe, scientists at Brookhaven National Laboratory reported today.
The unexpected findings, made with a particle accelerator at the laboratory, may be the first glimpse of a previously unseen kind of matter. If the findings are confirmed, the heart of subatomic theory, called the Standard Model, will be ''insufficient to describe our universe,'' said Dr. Thomas B. Kirk, Brookhaven's associate director for high energy and nuclear physics.
Though the results announced today throw cherished ideas into question, particle physicists have been waiting for such a development for years because it opens a door into new worlds of theory and experimentation.
The scientists, from a dozen institutions in Germany, Japan, Russia and the United States, cautioned in interviews and at a news conference here today that there was a slim chance the results were a statistical fluke and that the Standard Model, which has held up for 30 years, would remain unchallenged.
But they said the experiments, which involved painstaking measurements of about a billion rare particles called muons (pronounced MEW-ons), had so far determined with 99 percent probability that the accepted theory had been breached. They said they were already gathering and analyzing more data that could eliminate the one chance in a hundred that their results were a fluke.
Muons are subatomic cousins of electrons. In the experiments described today, physicists measured muons' responses to magnetic fields. The results showed a large departure from predictions, based on the Standard Model, of the way muons wobbled in a powerful magnetic field, Dr. Kirk said.
Dr. Gerald Gabrielse, a professor and chairman of the physics department at Harvard University, called the results ''tremendously exciting'' because of the possible explanations for the discrepancy.
''It could lead to a whole deeper understanding of how reality is put together,'' Dr. Gabrielse said.  Among the leading possible reasons for the difference, physicists said, would be the existence of previously undetected particles with strange properties affecting the way the muons wobbled, or precessed, in the magnetic field.
In the Brookhaven experiment, called E821, muons created by a particle accelerator known as the Alternating Gradient Synchroton were injected into a powerful magnetic field and the frequency of their wobble was measured precisely.
Physicists have long known that the wobble rate is affected by the properties of space itself. Under the laws of quantum mechanics, which rule the subatomic realm, apparently empty space is actually a sea of what scientists call ''virtual particles'' that briefly appear and disappear and can interact with muons.
The Standard Model shows scientists how to calculate the effect that all known particles in that sea should have on the wobble frequency; those predicted shifts have been measured and verified with great precision. But the new measurements differ from those predictions, suggesting that previously unknown particles are also lurking in that subatomic sea, said Dr. Lee Roberts, a professor of physics at Boston University who is one of the spokesmen for the experiment.
''This whole experiment is based on measuring the effect of these virtual particles,'' Dr. Roberts said. ''There's a possibility that new particles that haven't been observed could be contributing.''
While those particles are not predicted by the Standard Model and have never been seen directly in an experiment, their existence would not surprise theorists. Despite the  model's success in explaining decades of experimental data, theorists believe it has logical and aesthetic flaws and that its complicated structure is unlikely to represent natural law at its most fundamental level.
To solve those problems, some physicists have developed a grander and much more speculative theory called supersymmetry. That theory solves many of those problems, by positing the existence of new particles, called supersymmetric partners, for each of the known particles.
Those partners are predicted to be relatively massive for subatomic particles and interact weakly with ordinary matter, making them difficult both to produce and to detect. But their existence could account for the unexplained shift in the wobble frequency, said Dr. William J. Marciano, a theorist at Brookhaven.
''The most natural meaning of this kind of indication,'' Dr. Marciano said, ''would be superymmetry.'' The observed change in the frequency, he said, ''fits supersymmetry like a glove.''
Dr. Frank Wilczek, a physics professor at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, said that the new result, though not statistically airtight, did mesh with what he called other indirect suggestions that supersymmetry might be the correct way to extend and shore up the Standard Model.
''It would mean that in describing the world, we would need to add to the equations of the Standard Model,'' Dr. Wilczek said. ''And those additions make the whole thing much prettier, more unified and more beautiful.''
If the Brookhaven experiments are an indirect indication that supersymmetric particles exist, then the size of the observed effect suggests that they could be produced and detected directly in a new generation of particle accelerators that will soon begin collecting data, several theorists said.
The first new machine to go into operation will be the upgraded Tevatron accelerator at the Fermi National Accelerator Laboratory, outside Chicago, which will begin collecting data this spring.
''Certainly at the highest energy machines they will look in these energy ranges for these new particles,'' said Dr. Vernon Hughes, a Yale physicist who is a spokesman for the experiment.
Theorists said that they would also explore other ways of explaining the  data, like the possibility that particles believed to be elementary and indivisible are made of smaller entities, and that the structure of space itself may be more complex than mainstream physics assumes.
The new results were presented  today at a scientific colloquium by Dr. William M. Morse, a Brookhaven physicist who is a member of the experimental team and its resident spokesman.
The experiments begin when protons, electrically charged particles normally found in atomic nuclei, stream at nearly the speed of light and smash into a piece of nickel.
From the debris created by those collisions, physicists extract bunches containing thousands of muons. The scientists chose muons because, being more massive than electrons, they are more likely to interact with the relatively massive particles predicted by supersymmetry.
To make the measurements, the scientists relied on a quantum-mechanical property, called spin, that is shared by muons and other particles. Though the particles do not really spin, they do share some properties with an ordinary top. If the top's spin axis is not exactly vertical, it wobbles, or precesses, just as the muons do in a strong magnetic field.
The Brookhaven scientists observed precisely the frequency with which the muons wobbled, leading to the results presented today. Dr. Morse said that the team had already made observations of several billion muons, but had finished analyzing the results from only about a billion of them.
By coincidence, Dr. Hughes studied under Isidor I. Rabi, the Nobel Prize winner who uttered a memorable line when the muon was a surprise discovery in the 1930's.
''Who ordered that?'' Professor Rabi asked.
When asked for a corresponding reaction to the new finding, Dr. Hughes thought for a moment and said, ''The people who do supersymmetry ordered it.''
