Editorial Observer; The Pursuit of Innocence in the Golden State

I remember her vividly, a woman standing in the liquor aisle of a grocery store in a Sacramento suburb. She had a cigarette in one hand and with the other she placed a fifth of store-brand vodka in the grocery cart. I was 14, and it was a summer morning, 1966. My family had moved to California from Iowa only a week before, fresh as a load of turnips just lifted from the soil. I knew the woman was divorced by the way she held her cigarette, by the way she did not look around to see if anyone was watching when she took the vodka off the shelf. In Iowa, liquor was segregated in a state-owned store with all the sensory appeal of an auto-body shop. No one divorced, and smoking was, if nothing worse, a waste of matches.
Iowans moved to California in droves about then, and not to drink, divorce and smoke. They went for all the reasons people still go to California, for jobs and a less punishing climate and a new beginning. But one of the thrills of California, like seeing a line of palm trees or eating an artichoke or an avocado, was coming across a woman like that, a Tippi Hedren who converted what were vices in one state into the ordinary domestic manners of another and who implied, by her bearing, that if there was a problem, it was your problem. I look at Lisa Yuskavage's dewy, bosomy paintings, and I remember that California seemed exactly that voluptuous to me, its sins undone by the frankness with which they were revealed.
It was easy to believe that California was somehow defined by the casual license that woman embodied. But the woman, shopping for vodka, as it were, in her negligee, and the boy looking on, entranced and scandalized -- that is the true social and ethical dynamic of the golden state. It has always replicated, in its own way, the dynamic of America itself, a nation where some came to make a fresh start with a new rigor and others came to free themselves from rigor. If it could make electricity with the turbine of desire and disapproval, California would never run out of power.
Nowadays, no one dreams of lighting a cigarette in a California supermarket, and even the store-brand vodkas try to look as upscale as the Finnish and Swedish brands. Divorce is the common coin of modern sexuality, as the children of many of those Iowa-raised Californians grew up to discover for themselves. I remember how surprised I was to see farms when my family moved to California, when hops fields still grew on the southern outskirts of Sacramento. But California has been doing away with that unpleasant surprise for the past three decades. Now there are houses and houses and houses.
Electricity is a metaphorical form of energy as well as a literal one, a symbol, ever since the first kilowatt was generated, of human power over nature. There are, of course, complicated, interlacing causes for California's current energy crisis, rooted in bad planning and bad deregulatory designs. But one cause is the lack of human power over human nature, a growth in consumption fueled by an endless faith in repeated fresh starts, industrial and domestic. If you add up all of California's gospels -- the canons of social responsibility and individual liberty, of market freedom and unfettered growth -- you come up with a cumulative sense of innocence, which is one of the things that really gall the other Western states, which have come to understand California better than it understands itself.
Californians talk about nothing but change, because that is the landscape they live in. The rate of change is so rapid, and has been for so many years now, that the idea of conservation seems almost futile. Or rather, it seems commodified and impersonal, dependent on more efficient appliances, less consumptive houses and cleaner cars instead of altered behavior and wiser choices. California believes in innocence with the same fervor it believes in newness, in the psychology of starting over again. Electricity is the perfect metaphor for that easy faith. It is always new, always fresh, intangible and killing at the same time.
