From Light to Darkness: Astronomy's New Universe

A gasp went through the auditorium of the Space Telescope Science Institute on Wednesday when Dr. Adam Riess, a young astronomer from the institute, put the last mark on his so-called Hubble diagram, a plot of the brightness and speed of distant objects that astronomers use to divine the history of the universe.
The Darth Vaders of astronomy had gathered here to take stock of their expanding and increasingly dark realm. Once upon a time astronomy was about what could be seen in the sky, about jewel-like lights that moved in eternally recurring patterns and the soft glow of galaxies and comets.
Now it is about what cannot be seen. In the last few decades astronomers have had to confront the possibility that stars and galaxies -- not to mention the creatures that inhabit them -- are barely more than flecks of froth on a stormy sea of dark matter.
Now Dr. Riess was presenting his colleagues with evidence, based on observations of a star that exploded 11 billion years ago, that the universe -- dark matter and all -- was being blown apart under the influence of a mysterious antigravitational force known only as ''dark energy.''
''We are doing astronomy of the invisible,'' admitted Dr. Mario Livio, a theorist at the Space Telescope institute, who had organized the meeting, called ''The Dark Universe: Matter, Energy, and Gravity'' last fall.
As it turned out, the meeting coincided with a NASA news conference announcing the breakthrough discovery by Dr. Riess and his colleagues and thus was dominated by discussions of new telescopes in space and new dimensions in the universe as astronomers grappled with the meaning of dark energy and how to take its measure.
Now physicists, some of whom have been reluctant to take acceleration of the universe seriously, will have to explain what this dark energy is. ''Those numbers are alarming, and apparently true,'' said Dr. Michael Dine, a theoretical physicist from the University of California at Santa Cruz. He described his colleagues as now working ''frantically'' to find an explanation.
On one level, the universe, with all of its dark baggage, seems to make sense. The total amount of matter and energy seems to be just enough to guarantee  that the large-scale geometry of space-time is ''flat,'' or Euclidean, a result that cosmologists have long considered to be the most desirable and aesthetic. On the other hand, the detailed breakdown of the constituents of the cosmos is, as Dr. Livio says, ''ugly'' -- 65 percent dark matter, 30 percent dark matter of unknown nature and only 5 percent stars, gas and dust.
''We live in a preposterous universe,'' said Dr. Michael Turner, an astrophysicist at the University of Chicago. ''Dark energy. Who ordered that?''
Of course, it was Einstein who originally ordered dark energy when he inserted a fudge factor called the cosmological constant into his gravitational equations describing the universe. Lambda, as it is known, after the Greek letter, represented a sort of cosmic repulsion associated with space itself that kept the cosmos from collapsing of its own weight. Einstein abandoned the cosmological constant when it was discovered that the universe was expanding, and resisted efforts to bring it back, once referring to it as his biggest blunder.
But he couldn't keep it out forever. In 1998 two competing teams of astronomers trying to measure how the expansion of the universe was slowing down because of cosmic gravity, found that the universe was actually speeding up, as if the galaxies were being pushed apart by a force -- dubbed, in the spirit of the times, ''dark energy.''
''This was a very strange result,'' recalled Dr. Riess, who was a member of one of the teams. ''It was the opposite of what we thought we were doing.'' Was this Einstein's old cosmological constant, something even weirder or a mistake?
The effect had showed up as an unexpected dimness on the part of certain exploding stars known as supernovae that the astronomers were using as so-called standard candles, objects whose distance could be gauged from their apparent brightness. The astronomers deduced that these stars were farther away than  they should have been in an evenly expanding universe, and that therefore the expansion was actually accelerating.
But dust or chemical changes over the eons in the stars could also have dimmed the supernovae. The cleanest test of dark energy and the acceleration hypothesis, Dr. Riess explained, would be to find supernovae even farther out and back into the past, halfway or more back to the Big Bang itself. Because it is space itself that provides the repulsive push, according to Einstein's equations, that push should start out small when the universe is small and grow as the universe expands. Cosmic acceleration would only kick in when lambda's push got big enough to dominate the gravity of ordinary matter and energy in the universe, about five or six billion years ago. Before then the universe would have been slowing down, like a Mark McGwire blast that has not yet reached the top of its trajectory, and a supernova glimpsed at that great distance would appear relatively brighter than it should. If dust or chemical evolution were responsible, such distant stars should appear relatively even dimmer.
By chance the Hubble Space Telescope had observed a supernova in late 1997 and early 1998 that proved to be 11 billion light-years away -- the most distant yet seen. On Dr. Riess's Hubble diagram it appeared twice as bright as it should.
''Extraordinary claims require extraordinary evidence -- I hope the I.R.S. doesn't say that to you,'' Dr. Riess told his audience, but, he concluded, ''the cosmological constant looks good for this supernova.''
Dr. Livio said, ''A year ago probably a large fraction of the people in this room would not have believed it.''
But there were more complicated explanations, forms of dark energy other than the cosmological constant on physicists' drawing boards, as well as the possibility that astronomers were still being fooled. To explicate the nature of the dark energy, astronomers need to observe more supernovae as far back as 11 billion years ago, to cover the time when the universe began to accelerate.
''How fast did it go from deceleration to acceleration?'' asked Dr. Riess. Answering such questions could help astronomers determine how hard the dark energy is pushing on the universe compared with the predictions for the cosmological constant. A fast turnaround, he said, ''begins to tell you there is a lot of oomph for a given amount of 'it.' ''
''The cosmological constant is the benchmark oomph,'' he said.
To find those supernovae so far out cosmologists will have to go to space, said Dr. Saul Perlmutter, a physicist at the University of California's Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory and a veteran dark energy hunter.
On the ground, the supernova researchers have to employ a wide network of people and telescopes to detect the explosions, diagnose their type and then to watch them fade. Dr. Perlmutter described an orbiting  telescope that would perform all three functions. The Supernova/Acceleration Probe, or SNAP, would combine an 80-inch diameter mirror (only about 16 percent smaller than the Hubble), a giant electronic camera with a billion pixels and a special spectroscope.
If all goes well, Dr. Perlmutter said, the telescope could be launched in 2008. In three years of operation, he estimated, SNAP could harvest about 2,000 supernovae. To distinguish the different ideas about dark energy, observations would have to be refined to the level of 1 or 2 percent uncertainty .
''We're all excited,'' he said.
So are the physicists. Their list of suspects begins with Einstein's cosmological constant, but therein lies a problem. About the time that Einstein was abandoning it, quantum mechanics -- the set of rules that govern the subatomic realm -- was establishing a theoretical foundation for the cosmological constant. According to quantum theory, empty space should be foaming with temporary particles and their cumulative energy would outweigh the matter in the universe, including dark matter, by 120 orders of magnitude -- that is, a factor of 10 followed by 119 zeros. At that level, the force of the vacuum would either have crumpled the universe or blown it apart before even an atom had the chance to form.
The fact that the universe is in fact puttering along rather gently suggests that there is something fundamental about physics and the universe that physicists still don't know. Dr. Steven Weinberg, the Nobel Prize-winning particle theorist at the University of Texas, has called the cosmological constant ''the bone in our throat.'' If the dark energy really is Einstein's cosmological constant, then physicists have to answer questions like why it is so small -- roughly comparable, in fact, to the density of matter in our own epoch.
Lacking an answer so far, even from string theory, the mathematically daunting candidate theory of everything, some theorists have resorted to a controversial and somewhat philosophical notion called the anthropic principle, which, in effect, says that physicists need to factor in their own existence when they think about the universe. Out of all the possible universes that can be imagined, this line of thinking goes, the only ones in which humans can find themselves is one that is conducive to human life.
That means, Dr. Weinberg has  pointed out, that the cosmological constant has to be small enough to allow time for galaxies and stars to condense from the primordial fog before it takes over and starts blowing the universe apart.
Dr. Alex Vilenkin of Tufts University in Massachusetts pointed out to the Dark Universe audience that the universe was at its peak in making stars about five billion or six billion years ago, just about the time that dark energy and the matter density would have been equal. Our own sun, some 4.5 billion years old, was on the tale end of that wave, and now here we are. ''Observers are where the galaxies are,'' said Dr. Vilenkin. ''A typical observer will see a small cosmological constant.''
Many physicists are uncomfortable with this line of reasoning, and they are seeking the answer in different class of theories known as quintessence, after the Greek word for the fifth element. Modern physics, noted Dr. Paul Steinhardt, a theorist at Princeton, is replete with mysterious energy fields that would exhibit negative gravity. The trick, Dr. Steinhardt explained, is finding a field that would act like the dark energy without a lot of fudging on the part of theorists.
''The observations are forcing us to do this,'' he said. ''Dark energy is an interesting problem. Any solution is quite interesting.''
One theory that captured the fancy of the astronomers in Baltimore was a modification of gravity recently proposed by three string theorists at New York University: Dr. Gia Dvali, Dr. Gregory Gabadadze and Dr. Massimo Porrati. In string theory -- so named because it describes elementary particles as tiny vibrating strings -- the ordinary world is often envisioned as a three-dimensional island (a membrane, or ''brane'' in string jargon) floating in a 10- or 11-dimensional space. Ordinary particles like electrons and quarks and forces like electromagnetism are confined to three dimensions, to the brane, but gravity is not.
As a result, Dr. Dvali suggested that gravity could only travel so far through conventional space before it leaked off into the extra dimensions, thereby weakening itself. To an observer in the traditional three dimensions it looks as if the universe is accelerating. The cosmological constant, in effect, he said, is a kind of gravitational brane drain. ''Gravity fools itself,'' he said. ''It sees itself as a cosmological constant.''
Dr. Dvali's theory was welcomed by the astronomers as a sign that string theory was beginning to come down from its ivory tower of abstraction and make useful, testable predictions about the real world. (In another string contribution, Dr. Steinhardt introduced a new theory of the early universe, in which the Big Bang is set off by a pair of branes clashing together like cymbals.)
Afterward Dr. Riess and Dr. Perlmutter pressed Dr. Dvali on what they would see when they looked out past the crossover point where gravity began falling out of the world; would the transition between a decelerating universe and an accelerating one happen more abruptly than in the case of the cosmological constant? Dr. Dvali said he hadn't done any calculations, but he said it was his ''naïve guess'' that the crossover would happen more smoothly than in a lambda world.
''I'd love to see this guy do some Hubble diagrams,'' Dr. Riess said.
Even if Dr. Dvali could be coaxed into providing a prediction, however, success in identifying the dark energy was not guaranteed to the astronomers. Calling himself a spokesman for the ''cranky point of view,'' Dr. Steinhardt pointed out that the oft-proclaimed era of ''precision cosmology'' was bound to have its limits. Other cosmological parameters, particularly the cosmic density of matter in the universe, were not likely to be known well enough for even SNAP to untangle the models in which the quintessence varied over time. Worried that the overselling of SNAP could sap astronomers' will to come up with new ideas, he said, ''We should try to make as few pronouncements as possible.''
Dr. Turner refused to be swayed from his ''irrational exuberance.'' Appealing to the astronomers' pride, he urged them to be ambitious. ''We have a chance to do fundamental physics here,'' he said. ''Let's see if we can crack this nut. Maybe we'll fall on our faces. Maybe cranky Paul is right.
''I still have a lot of youthful juices in my body.''
