Mental Decline Is Linked To Heart Bypass Surgery

Five years after heart bypass surgery, 42 percent of patients show a significant decline on tests of mental ability, probably from brain damage caused by the surgery, doctors from Duke University say in a new study.
Older patients and those with a drop in test scores soon after surgery were most likely to show declines five years later. The report, being published today in The New England Journal of Medicine, has evoked mixed reactions among experts.
On the one hand, they say that a lowered test score does not necessarily mean a person is mentally impaired and that the 42 percent figure might needlessly frighten patients away from surgery that could save their lives. On the other hand, researchers concede that the study was done well and that it highlights an ugly truth that surgeons know but are not eager to discuss with patients: some patients do wind up mentally impaired after bypass surgery. And doctors are not sure why, though they suspect various factors that interfere with blood flow to the brain during surgery.
The findings also seem likely to fuel the debate about whether all of the approximately 500,000 bypass operations done each year in the United States are necessary, or whether more patients with blocked arteries, particularly older people, should be treated with medication or less invasive procedures to open clogged blood vessels.
The researchers are not the first to link mental decline to bypass operations. But earlier studies were shorter term, and many doctors hoped that the cognitive losses would be temporary. The new study is the first to show lasting changes in so many patients so long after the surgery.
The study, based on 261 patients who had bypass surgery at Duke from 1989 to 1993, relied on mental tests done before surgery and then six weeks, six months and five years later. The patients' average age was 61, with a range of 50 to 71. Patients were considered to have declined mentally if their test performance at five years was at least 20 percent lower than their score before surgery. A 20 percent drop was similar to the difference in function between subjects at ages 40 and 60.
The drop in scores in the bypass patients could not be attributed to aging, the authors said, because it was more than two to three times the mental decline found in 5,888 Medicare patients who did not have bypass surgery and whose cognitive abilities were followed for five years in a separate study.
A doctor not associated with the study, William A. Baumgartner, chief of cardiac surgery at Johns Hopkins Hospital, said researchers at his hospital were also studying the problem but had found far fewer patients with significant long-term problems, perhaps 8 percent to 10 percent.
''I was shocked at the 42 percent,'' Dr. Baumgartner said. ''We just haven't seen that in our five-year follow-up. People who read this thing are going to be scared out of their minds that they're going to be some kind of invalid. In our series, that is clearly not the case. They need further work to see how this affects the well-being of patients.''
Dr. Mark F. Newman, an author of the study and chief of cardiothoracic anesthesiology at Duke University Medical Center, said researchers were not sure how many of the patients were troubled by their declines or even aware of them, since the changes might not cause problems in their daily lives.
But Dr. Newman said he hoped the findings would not lead patients to shun bypass surgery. ''In a lot of patients, we prolong their life,'' he said. ''We have to continue working on improving the quality of their life as well.''
Several elements of bypass surgery can potentially cause brain damage, Dr. Newman said. One is the heart-lung machine, through which the patient's blood is circulated to pick up oxygen. Doctors suspect air bubbles produced by the machine may block blood flow through minute vessels in the skull, killing brain cells. The machine may also pump droplets of fat released from the surgical site to the brain, where they can cause the same problem as air bubbles. It is also possible that the machine does not provide enough oxygen for some patients.
The other possible source of trouble is fatty deposits in the patient's own aorta, the large vessel that carries blood out of the left side of the heart. Surgeons clamp the aorta and may sew blood vessels to it during bypass surgery; those procedures can break off deposits, which may then travel to the patient's head and block blood flow.
Dr. Newman said newer techniques in which the surgery was done without the machine, and with little or no manipulation of the aorta, might help to protect the brain. But not all patients are candidates for the new techniques. In the United States, about 20 percent of bypass operations are done without the heart-lung machine. The machine will always be needed for some types of cases, Dr. Newman said, and for that reason researchers are trying to develop drugs that patients can be given during surgery to help brain cells tolerate declines in blood pressure and oxygen level that cannot always be avoided during surgery.
But other researchers say it is not clear that the heart-lung machine should take all the blame. Dr. Ola A. Selnes, a neuropsychologist at Johns Hopkins, who wrote an editorial in the same issue, said other studies had shown cognitive declines in elderly patients who had operations not involving the heart; the stress of anesthesia and major surgery may have been too much for them.
Dr. Selnes noted that cognitive problems in bypass patients might be partly due to their underlying vascular disease, which affects blood vessels all over the body.
A weakness of the study, and of earlier ones, is the lack of a control group -- a set of patients who do not have bypass surgery but who have vascular disease similar to that in the surgical patients and who match them in age, sex, race, education level, lifestyle and so on. Only by comparing two such groups over time could researchers find out how much mental decline is due to bypass surgery and how much to vascular disease. Dr. Selnes said such a study was under way.
When answers do become available, Dr. Selnes said, it might be possible to identify patients who are particularly at risk for cognitive problems, and to suggest alternative treatments to bypass surgery. ''Not everyone has to have bypass,'' Dr. Selnes said. ''There are choices. Of these 600,000 being done very year, only a subset really require what you might call emergency surgery.''
Other patients, he said, could be offered medical treatment or less invasive procedures like balloon angioplasty to open clogged vessels.
''There has been a kind of blind faith that bypass is the ultimate answer to any kind of heart disease, and I think that has to be rethought,'' Dr. Selnes said.
