Panel Recommends Ending Satellite Plan

At the urging of its Republican leadership, the House Appropriations Committee is recommending canceling an expensive infrared satellite system that the Pentagon considers vital to missile defense.
The satellites are intended to track ballistic missiles as they soar through the atmosphere, providing data that would help interceptor missiles tell missiles from decoys and  home in on and destroy warheads.
The Pentagon had proposed putting two dozen such satellites, at an estimated cost of $11 billion to $20 billion, into low orbits above the earth over the next two decades to provide continuous surveillance against missile attacks.
But in a report that has yet to be voted on by the full House, the Appropriations Committee contends that the satellite program is over its budget and behind schedule. It also cites an internal Pentagon study that questions the effectiveness of the satellites in discriminating between warheads and decoys.
Noting that ground-based radar might be a less expensive alternative to the satellites, the committee recommended denying the Bush administration's entire request of $385 million for the satellite program in the fiscal year that began on Oct. 1. Instead, the committee proposed transferring most of that money to other satellite and radar programs.
''This was not ready to move forward,'' said Jim Specht, a spokesman for Representative Jerry Lewis, a California Republican who is chairman of the Pentagon subcommittee of the House Appropriations Committee.
''By taking away the funding, the committee is making clear they need to do more development and testing of this system in order for it to become an integral part of national missile defense,'' Mr. Specht added.
But Pentagon officials said that canceling or sharply cutting the satellite program would be a major setback to the Bush administration's missile defense plan.
''It would degrade the future capability of the overall missile defense program,'' said Lt. Col. Rick Lehner, a spokesman for the Pentagon's Ballistic Missile Defense Organization.
''Ground-based systems are limited by the curvature of the earth,'' Colonel Lehner added. ''They don't have the range of a space-based system, which can cover the whole planet.''
Congressional officials said the fate of the satellite program before the full House and in the Senate was unclear. The Senate Armed Services Committee has voted to reduce the program by $96.6 million, while the Senate Appropriations Committee has yet to vote on the Pentagon spending bills.
The satellites, known as the space-based infrared system-low, are being developed by two competing teams,  one led by TRW and Raytheon, the other by Spectrum Astro and Northrop Grumman.
The system had its roots in the  Reagan administration's Strategic Defense Initiative, when it was known as Brilliant Eyes. Using infrared sensors, the satellites are intended to locate warheads when they reach the mid-course of their trajectory, sending back to earth data that would help ground-based radars and interceptor rockets to fix on a threatening warhead.
Proponents contend that the satellites would be valuable not just for tracking long-range nuclear-tipped missiles, but also short-range weapons, known as theater missiles, that could be fired at American troops overseas.
''It's an essential component if ballistic missile defenses are to work effectively,'' said Representative John Spratt, a South Carolina Democrat who supports the program. ''Not just for national missile defense, but also theater missile defense.''
Pentagon officials have often cited the infrared satellites in responding to critics who contend that a missile shield would be easily fooled by decoys released alongside warheads in space. By identifying the difference in temperature between a decoy and warhead, the satellites would, in theory, be able to guide an interceptor toward the real target, the Pentagon contends.
Critics of missile defense question whether any system would be effective in picking out decoys. But they concede that a missile defense is likely to be more effective with the infrared satellites than without them.
''The job of the attacker is easier if there is not a S.B.I.R.S.-low system,'' said Lisbeth Gronlund, senior staff scientist at the Union of Concerned Scientists, an arms control group.
But over the years, the satellite program has been repeatedly criticized by Congressional investigators and Pentagon testers.
In a report released in February, the General Accounting Office, Congress's investigative arm, asserted that the satellite program was being rushed and was likely to face technical failures and major cost overruns.
The investigators found, for example, that the Pentagon was proposing to launch the first satellites before critical software had been completed.
''The S.B.I.R.S.-low program is at high risk of not delivering the system on time or at cost or with expected performance,'' the report concluded.
