In Spiders, Itsy Bitsy Gets the Girl

In the battle for mates, it is the largest males of the animal kingdom that tend to dominate, facing down competitors with their towering height and great girth. But scientists have discovered one battle that conveys the advantage to the teeny-tiny male: the battle with gravity.
Scientists at the University of Kentucky have provided one of the best explanations yet for the astonishingly small size of some males. It is a question that has puzzled researchers, including Darwin, for more than a century.
The higher up the female spiders spin their webs, the researchers say, the greater the heights the males must scale to reach them, and the smaller these fellows tend to be.
''If you're small, you climb better,'' said Dr. Jordi Moya-Laraño, a spider ecologist at Kentucky who was the lead author of the new study. The idea is simple. The less weight one has to haul along on a climb, the easier and quicker it is.
The research was published in a recent issue of the Evolution in an article titled ''Climbing to Reach Females: Romeo Should Be Small.''
Researchers who were not involved with the study called the so-called gravity hypothesis a creative answer to this peculiarly spider-centric puzzle. While males in other groups can be dwarfed by their females, female spiders often heavily outweigh their mates. In fact, Dr. Moya-Laraño said spiders exhibited the most radical size differences between the sexes of any land animals, with females sometimes weighing 100 times as much as their males.
Dr. Maydianne Andrade, a behavioral ecologist at the University of Toronto at Scarborough, noted that the hypothesis was not necessarily limited to spiders, and might also explain other small males, including tiny male insects that perform airborne acrobatics during courtship and might maneuver more easily because they are small.
To test the gravity hypothesis, Dr. Moya-Laraño and colleagues compared the life patterns and sizes of 112 species of spiders.
They found that if females made their webs or prowled about on the ground, a huge, lumbering male appeared to be at little disadvantage. But the higher the females lived, in shrubs or up in the trees, the smaller, relatively, males tended to be. And the bigger the species -- meaning the more weight a male would have to drag skyward -- the more drastically males appeared to have become diminished relative to their gargantuan mates.
But, researchers noted, it is likely that other forces are also helping to exaggerate the difference in sizes between the spider sexes. In some cases, it may be more a matter of gigantism in females that need to be large to produce a bounty of eggs, than dwarfism in males. And gravity aside, spider males may find great benefits in being negligibly small, particularly those males that must seduce hungry females waiting to pounce on intruders at the web.
Noting the vast number of cannibalistic spider species, Dr. Andrade said: ''The risk is that the female will consume you before you mate. Small spiders can dance across the web without the female detecting their vibrations.''
Understandably, spider suitors can be quite tentative in their approach and, scientists who have seen the carnage, can find themselves squeamish. Darwin himself once noted how a male spider ''in the midst of his preparatory caresses was seized by the object of his attractions, enveloped by her in a web and then devoured.''
