One Cosmic Question, Too Many Answers

Call it the theory of anything.
Einstein once wondered aloud whether ''God had any choice'' in creating the universe. It was his fondest hope that the answer was no.
He and subsequent generations of physicists have hoped that at the end of their labors there would be one answer -- a so-called Theory of Everything -- that would explain why the details of the world are the way they are and cannot be any other way: why there was a Big Bang, the number of dimensions of space-time, the masses of elementary particles.
For 20 years, physicists have lodged those hopes in string theory, a mathematically labyrinthian effort to portray nature as made up of tiny wriggling strings and membranes, rather than pointlike particles or waves.
Once called a piece of 21st-century physics that had fallen into the 20th century by accident, string theory has become one of the hippest fields of science, celebrated in books like the recent best seller ''The Elegant Universe,'' by the Columbia theorist Brian Greene, and the subject of a miniseries on ''Nova,'' coming this fall.
In principle, strings can unite all the forces of nature, including gravity, in a single mathematical framework. But the ''stringiness'' of nature manifests itself only at energies and temperatures that can be generated in a particle accelerator the size of a small galaxy.
As a result, physicists have been left at the mercy of their mathematical imaginations or sifting cosmological data for hints of a clue from God's own particle accelerator, the Big Bang.
The hope was that when all was said and done, there would be only one solution to the theory's tangled equations, one answer corresponding to only one possible universe. But recent progress in string theory paradoxically seems to leave physics further than ever from that dream of a unique answer. Instead of a single answer, the equations of string theory seem to have so many solutions, millions upon millions of them, each describing a logically possible universe, that it may be impossible to tell which one describes our own.
In a series of conceptual and technical breakthroughs, a group of theorists at Stanford showed this year that string theory could describe a universe whose expansion was accelerating -- something that many experts thought impossible.
That was no small accomplishment because cosmologists now theorize that some puzzling and so far unidentified ''dark energy'' is wrenching space apart ever more violently. This energy seems to make up 70 percent of the cosmos, according to astronomical observations.
The new calculations suggest that this dark energy cannot last forever, that it will disappear sometime in the far future, according to the researchers, Dr. Shamit Kachru, Dr. Renata Kallosh and Dr. Andrei Linde, all of Stanford, and Dr. Sandip P. Trivedi of the Tata Institute of Fundamental Research in Bombay.
But the same calculations confirmed that string theory could have a vast number of solutions, each representing a different universe with slightly different laws of physics. The detailed characteristics of any particular one of these universes -- the laws that describe the basic forces and particles -- might be decided by chance.
As a result, string theorists and cosmologists are confronted with what Dr. Leonard Susskind of Stanford has called ''the cosmic landscape,'' a sort of metarealm of space-times. Contrary to Einstein's hopes, it may be that neither God nor physics chooses among these possibilities, Dr. Susskind contends. Rather it could be life.
Only a fraction of the universes in this metarealm would have the lucky blend of properties suitable for life, Dr. Susskind explained. It should be no surprise that we find ourselves in one of these.
''We live where we can live,'' he said.
Dr. Susskind conceded that many colleagues who harbor the Einsteinian dream of predicting everything are appalled by that notion that God plays dice with the laws of physics.
Among them is Dr. David Gross, director of the Kavli Institute of Theoretical Physics in Santa Barbara, Calif., who said, ''I'm a total Einsteinian with respect to the ultimate goal of science.''
Physicists should be able to predict all the parameters of nature, Dr. Gross said, adding, ''They're not adjustable.''
But Dr. Max Tegmark, a cosmologist at the University of Pennsylvania, said, ''I think this grand dream is basically dying.''
Dr. Michael Douglas of Rutgers and the Institute of Advanced Scientific Studies, near Paris, called the plethora of string universes ''the Alice's Restaurant'' problem.
''You can get anything you want at Alice's Restaurant,'' he said. ''Is this a theory of something, very many things or nothing? That's what we're trying to establish.''
The Early Hopes  Not Particles, But Strings
The question of whether strings will provide a unique answer to the universe has been hanging over physicists' heads ever since the modern form of string theory made its triumphal emergence in 1984. That year, Dr. John Schwarz of the California Institute of Technology and Dr. Michael Green, now of Cambridge University in England, showed that thinking of elementary particles as little strings instead of points eliminated troublesome mathematical anomalies from theories that sought to combine gravity with subatomic physics.
Even Einstein had failed to unite those disparate and mathematically incompatible realms. But the 1984 calculation raised the hope that physicists had finally found the key to the so-called Theory of Everything.
''There was this wild enthusiasm, unbridled enthusiasm, that we paid for later,'' said Dr. Andrew Strominger, a professor of physics at Harvard.
In 1985, Dr. Strominger, Dr. Edward Witten of the Institute for Advanced Study in Princeton, Dr. Gary T. Horowitz, now at the University of California at Santa Barbara, and Dr. Philip Candelas, now at the University of Texas, published a classic paper showing that it was possible to construct a string theory consistent with the so-called Standard Model that describes particles and forces in our four-dimensional universe.
One problem is that string theory requires 10 dimensions of space-time, whereas we appear to live in four. Dr. Strominger remembered being excited when he found a paper by the mathematician Dr. Shing-Tung Yau, now of Harvard and the Chinese University of Hong Kong. It proved a conjecture by Dr. Eugenio Calabi, now retired from the University of Pennsylvania, that the extra dimensions could be curled up in microscopically invisible ways like the loops in a carpet.
The paper described only one way this folding could be done. But Dr. Yau soon told the physicists that there were thousands of what are now called Calabi-Yau spaces, each one representing a different solution of the string equations. By the time their paper was finished, ''the uniqueness of string theory was certainly already in question,'' Dr. Strominger said.
That was just the beginning. For each of the thousands of ways of curling the extra dimensions into Calabi-Yau spaces, there were hundreds of variations in details like the sizes of the loops and the way electrical and magnetic fields thread through them. When the variations are taken into account, the number of solutions and the number of possible universes can easily exceed 10 100.
The Challenge  A Universe Unfit For Life or Physics?
This bounty of possibilities makes it extremely daunting for scientists who want to test string theory by comparing its predictions to the real world. One telltale clue to the right answer, as well as a huge challenge, developed five years ago when astronomers discovered that the expansion of the universe was apparently accelerating. But until recently, many theorists doubted that strings could produce even one example of an accelerating universe.
The reason is that the leading explanation for this behavior is a cosmic repulsion, known as the cosmological constant, that results from the properties of empty space itself.
It was first invented by Einstein in 1917 as a fudge factor to stabilize the universe and then abandoned by him when astronomers found out that the universe was not static, but expanding.
If Einstein's fudge factor is real after all, the universe will continue to expand faster and faster as space grows bigger and bigger, producing more and more repulsion.
String theorists did not know how to deal with the cosmological constant. According to quantum mechanics, the weird laws that govern subatomic physics, empty space should be foaming with energy and particles that wink in and out of existence, and their collective effect could produce a repulsive force like Einstein's constant. But the calculations also suggest that this force should be some 1060  times what astronomers have measured; it would have blown the universe apart in its first millisecond, long before atoms, galaxies or humans could form.
Moreover, a permanently accelerating universe would present deep conceptual problems, several physicists pointed out, including Dr. Thomas Banks of Rutgers and the University of California at Santa Cruz, Dr. Willy Fischler of the University of Texas, Dr. Susskind and Dr. Witten.
Such a universe would slowly empty itself of energy and information because most of the galaxies would eventually be flying away so fast that humans could not see them. The observable universe would actually shrink, as if surrounded by a black hole. Life would become impossible, and the usual methods of formulating physics might not apply.
As a result of such arguments, it was widely presumed that a universe that accelerated forever -- that is, one with a cosmological constant -- was incompatible with string theory, Dr. Kachru of Stanford said.
It was partly to counter such claims, he added, that he and his colleagues were motivated to look for the cosmological constant in the gazillions of possible string universes.
The Hitch  A Breakthrough, But a Bleak One
Last winter, Dr. Kachru and his colleagues succeeded in using string theory to construct universes that accelerated, but with a surprising twist.
The hitch, in each case, was that the acceleration would be only temporary. It might last an extremely long time, but eventually the dark energy of the cosmological constant would melt away, decaying just in time to avoid the problems of permanent acceleration that string theorists have worried about. The universe would then coast for the rest of eternity.
The work followed on previous work by Dr. Kachru with Dr. Joseph Polchinski of the Santa Barbara Institute and Dr. Steven Giddings of the University of California at Santa Barbara, and by Dr. Polchinski and Dr. Raphael Bousso of the University of California at Berkeley.
Part of the reason dark energy decays, explained Dr. Linde of Stanford, is that these solutions describe the four-dimensional universe we observe around us -- three dimensions of space and one of time -- with the other six curled up so tightly that they cannot provide closet space. But it takes energy to keep the extra dimensions confined.
''In the long run,'' he said, ''the universe doesn't want to be four-dimensional. It wants to be 10 dimensions.''
So sooner or later, the loops will unravel like a tangle of rubber bands, passing through a succession of configurations that take less and less energy to maintain, until finally the other dimensions expand and the cosmological constant is gone.
The decay of the cosmological constant will be fatal, astronomers agree. At that moment a bubble of 10-dimensional space will sweep out at the speed of light, rearranging physics and the prospects of atoms and planets, not to mention biological creatures.
''What it leaves behind,'' Dr. Susskind said, ''it's hard to say. Almost certainly not a livable universe.''
The Role of Luck  A Controversial Idea Returns to Stage
The universe is certainly livable now, but why has long been a vexing and polarizing issue. Life as We Know It seems to require an almost miraculous juggling of a few atomic and astronomical parameters.
Was the universe designed for us? Or did we just get lucky?
Searching for answers, some theorists have invoked the so-called anthropic principle, which states that our universe has to have laws suitable for life. Otherwise we would not be here to see it. The apparent ''fine-tuning'' of this universe is simply an artifact of our own existence here as observers, Dr. Brandon Carter, now at the Paris Observatory in Meudon, argued in 1974.
The principle fits well with recent theories of the Big Bang that suggest that the universe seen through telescopes is just one in an endless chain of bubble universes that sprout from one another.
If there is just one universe, the fact that it suits us would seem suspiciously lucky. But if there are many universes to choose from, our existence is less miraculous.
It might be the diversity of string-theory universes that gives this metacosmos a chance at harboring life, Dr. Susskind says.
He likes to portray it as a mountain range, the ''cosmic landscape,'' in which the height of the peaks represents the energy or the cosmological constant of that configuration. The universe is like water rolling around the hills, always seeking a lower state. There are valleys and basins and plateaus where it can rest. But it can spread, plopping like a wave sloshing over the hills from valley to valley, from one configuration of dimensions and fields to another.
As a result, he said, in whatever form it starts, the universe will branch out into other forms. If it keeps sloshing, it will eventually land in a valley with the lucky mix of cosmic constants that allows for galaxies and carbon-based chemistry somewhere. If a small fraction of the subuniverses can support life, then there is a good chance that life will arise somewhere, Dr. Susskind explained.
Others caution, however, that it has not been proved that different classes of universes would be so interconnected. ''It could be that there are many disconnected landscapes,'' explained Dr. Douglas of Rutgers.
Dr. Susskind said that ''whether we like it or not,'' the new findings gave further credence to the anthropic principle and a mathematical framework for how it might work.
But such ''anthropic thinking'' is defeatist to many physicists. ''We see this kind of thing happen over and over again as a reaction to difficult problems,'' Dr. Gross said. ''Come up with a grand principle that explains why you're unable to solve the problem.''
The notion that some problems are unsolvable is discouraging to the younger generation, he said, pointing out that nobody even knows what the final form of string theory will be.
Dr. Witten said he also disliked the anthropic principle. ''I continue to hope that we are overlooking or misunderstanding something and that there is ultimately a more unique answer,'' he wrote by e-mail.
Dr. Susskind conceded that he had once been on the other side of the question.
''I've had myself jerked around by this theory,'' he said. ''When you have to give up your fondest dream for what the theory would do'' -- a reference to the quest for a unique answer -- ''that's a hard thing to swallow.''
The Future  Still Listening For Orderly Music
Dr. Strominger of Harvard said the debate on anthropic principle was indicative of the ''all-or-nothing psychology'' of string theory.
''It's not enough to solve some problems,'' he said. ''It has to solve every problem.''
Theorists have long hoped that all but one of these solutions will eliminate themselves through some mathematical inconsistency or failure to reproduce an essential feature of the universe like the cosmological constant. Dr. Douglas of Rutgers has challenged that hope, saying string theory may have so many solutions that physical measurements can not distinguish among them.
Indeed, he pointed out in a recent paper, it has not been proved that string theory does not have an infinite number of solutions. So far, anything seems possible.
Rather than sifting myriad solutions for the one that fits our universe, Dr. Douglas has developed statistical methods to analyze the set of string solutions as a whole to find patterns that will not show up when the solutions are examined one by one.
The results could help ascertain which features of this ''zoo of possibilities'' are more common and which are more rare, and how many solutions really are too many.
''My own philosophy,'' Dr. Douglas said in an interview, ''is that we should do our best to listen to what string theory is trying to tell us. It is smarter than we are.''
Dr. Kachru suggested that it might be wishful thinking to expect that a ''smoking gun'' confirmation of string theory could be found from comparing it to today's universe. The full glories of string theory, he said, manifest themselves only at energies trillions of times what earthbound particle accelerators can produce.
Perhaps, he said, theorists should be looking for the smoking gun in the Big Bang.
Asked what the smoking-gun question might be, Dr. Kachru laughed and said, ''If I knew, I would be working in that field.''
