What Did We Learn From AIDS?

If AIDS is any indication, the plagues that await us in the future are certain to leave scientists far wiser than they are today.
Two decades of grappling with AIDS have taught scientists not only arcane lessons about the molecules that cause illness and the molecules that can treat it, but also some basic truths about the politics, economics, and psychology of health and disease.
AIDS exploded a scientific complacency that seems inconceivably naïve today. Few experts were ruminating about new plagues in the 1970's because it was widely assumed that vaccination, sanitation and antibiotics were making infections obsolete. The retroviruses, the family of viruses that includes the AIDS virus, H.I.V., were felt to be of academic interest only.
''The consensus was that retroviruses did not infect humans, that viruses did not cause cancer and that infectious diseases were a problem for the third world but not for us,'' said Dr. Robert C. Gallo, co-discoverer of the AIDS virus, who now directs the Institute of Human Virology at the University of Maryland Biotechnology Institute in Baltimore. ''Those biases were shattered in just a few years.''
The chain of medical events unleashed by H.I.V. is unique. The virus causes a turmoil in the body from the moment of infection on, appropriating enzymes in the infected person's own cells to spawn billions more viruses daily. These penetrate every human tissue and slowly destroy the integrity of the body's immune system.
The infected person can transmit the disease to others but looks and feels well: the infection is largely invisible until its last stages, a decade or more afterward, when a depleted immune system leaves its owner vulnerable to a range of infections and cancers. Drugs that stop the virus from replicating can keep infected people healthy but will not eradicate the infection.
In the years it took to figure this all out, experts in virtually every corner of science learned important lessons.
In addition to valuable nuances of cell biology, virologists have learned that viral infections can indeed be treated, Dr. Gallo said. Before AIDS, only a few primitive antiviral drugs existed. Most scientists thought that, because viruses use the body's cellular machinery to reproduce, developing better ones would be so difficult as to be ''almost hopeless,'' as well as prohibitively costly. With AIDS, the clear need for drugs outstripped the naysaying, and the success of the anti-H.I.V. drugs became a milestone in antiviral treatment.
Immunologists now have a far better understanding of the primary immune cells called T-lymphocytes that the virus particularly strikes, said Dr. Fred T. Valentine, a professor of medicine, infectious diseases and immunology at New York University. The complex links between cancer, immunity and infection have also been cemented by findings in H.I.V.-infected people, he said. And AIDS has re-educated the scientists in the importance of vaccines, he said.
Lessons at the bedside have been no less striking. AIDS taught doctors to be suspicious of their patients' private lives, delving for intimate autobiographical details -- a brief experiment with drugs, an unwise sexual encounter -- they would never have pursued in years past. AIDS has also taught them to be suspicious of their patients' blood, that supremely dangerous weapon: the disease forced complete overhauls of standard protocols for blood drawing, blood transfusion and organ transplantation, not to mention surgery and dentistry. Thanks to AIDS, a box of latex gloves now appears at every hospital bedside.
But if AIDS alienated doctors from patients with rude questions and latex barriers, it bound them together in other ways. In the early years of the epidemic, it rekindled many doctors' interest in the almost lost art of caring for dying patients. They were untethered from useless, life-prolonging machinery and allowed to die quietly. Medical ethicists agree that AIDS was a prime force in introducing living wills, health care proxies, do-not-resuscitate orders and hospice care into common parlance.
While patients dying from AIDS taught doctors some lessons, people living with it taught them others. AIDS has been the first disease on record to spawn a huge, vocal, visible, angry grass-roots patients' rights movement that managed to change the course of medical history.
Agitating for better, more available treatments, activists changed the process of drug approval in the United States, prompting the Food and Drug Administration to create a fast track for the rapid release of lifesaving medications. They changed the structure of scientific meetings, which now routinely allow patients to attend and participate. They changed the balance of power in doctors' offices, becoming collaborators in their own care -- a philosophy that has carried over to people with many other diseases.
AIDS taught scientists to look past their laboratory doors to a world that is both smaller and bigger than they may assume. The world has become so small that an African in the bush, a peasant in rural China and a prep-schooled, Ivy Leagued systems analyst in Manhattan can all see a doctor for exactly the same complaints, can all be given the same AIDS diagnosis and can all be recommended the same medications. The world is still so big that only one of these people will be treated.
''AIDS has taught us both the power of science and its limitations,'' said Dr. Gerald Friedland, professor of medicine at Yale and director of the AIDS program there. ''It has given us incredible technologic successes. But fully implementing those successes still escapes us.''
