The Columbia Space Shuttle's Crew of 6 Americans and 1 Israeli

Seven astronauts, six Americans and an Israeli, died aboard the shuttle Columbia yesterday. Of the crew of five men and two women, four had never flown in space before.
Dr. Laurel Salton Clark  After Sea and Sky, Moving On to Space
Laurel Salton Clark had conquered the sea, diving with the Navy Seals and conducting medical evacuations from submarines off Scotland. She had penetrated the air as a flight surgeon aboard the Marine Attack Squadron of the Year.
Space was the logical next frontier.
''She was never one of these people to say, 'O.K., I found what I want to do,' it was always, 'What's the next challenge?' '' said Dr. Clark's younger brother, Daniel Salton. ''She was one of these people who just had goals, just saw the goal, the end result, and knew how much work it would take to get there and was willing to do it.''
Dr. Clark, 41, a Navy commander who was one of two women among the seven astronauts aboard the space shuttle Columbia, was always scuba diving or mountain biking, hiking or rock climbing or parachuting. She grew up in Racine, Wisc., the eldest of four children, married a fellow Navy officer, Jonathan Clark, who later joined her in working at NASA, and had an 8-year-old son, Iain.
In an e-mail message sent from the space shuttle a few days ago, Dr. Clark marveled at the view of Wind Point, a peninsula jutting into Lake Michigan a few miles from her childhood home, and wondered whether the photographs she had taken would turn out.
''Hello from above our magnificent planet earth,'' Dr. Clark wrote to a group of close friends and relatives. ''The perspective is truly awe-inspiring. Even the stars have a special brightness. I have seen my 'friend' Orion several times.''
An animal lover who was always the child to sleep with the family cat, Laurel Blair Salton graduated from Racine's William Horlick High School in 1979 and majored in zoology at the University of Wisconsin, in Madison, intending to be a veterinarian. Instead, she attended the university's medical school, where she was part of a tight-knit group of six friends who saved up their vacation time and spent the last three weeks before graduation in 1987 sailing a 42-foot boat through the British Virgin Islands.
After nearly a decade in the Navy, with postings in Pensacola, Fla., Holy Loch, Scotland, and Yuma, Ariz., a friend suggested that Dr. Clark take the NASA test. Like many others, she was not accepted on the first round. She later became part of a class known as the Sardines, because it had more than 40 astronaut candidates, the most in history, Mr. Salton said.
At NASA, Dr. Clark was nicknamed ''Floral,'' because of the vibrant colors that she wore when not in uniform.
Mr. Salton said he never worried about the safety of the shuttle -- until two weeks ago, when he joined his mother, siblings and several of Dr. Clark's friends at the launching.
''I was just an emotional wreck when she was in space, when you actually see that rocket go up,'' he recalled. ''Visions of the Challenger go through your head and you pray that it's not going to happen. Once they're up in space, big sigh of relief, O.K., the dangerous part is over. I never even considered that something could happen on the way down.''
While in space, Dr. Clark was part of several life-science experiments. In an interview from space published on Friday in The Milwaukee Journal Sentinel, she spoke of watching the sunsets.
''There's a flash -- the whole payload bay turns this rosy pink,'' she said. ''It only lasts about 15 seconds and then it's gone. It's very ethereal and extremely beautiful.''
Always a lover of her Scottish heritage, Dr. Clark had chosen as her wake-up song aboard the shuttle a bagpipe version of ''Amazing Grace,'' similar to one played at her wedding.
It will also be played at her funeral.
JODI WILGOREN
LOSS OF THE SHUTTLE: THE ASTRONAUTS
