Intriguing Intricacies From the Mars Rocks

Gusev Crater and Meridiani Planum, the exploration sites for NASA's twin rovers Spirit and Opportunity, are on opposite sides of Mars and are as different as New York City and the Illinois prairie. Gusev Crater is rocks, rocks everywhere. Meridiani Planum is flat, almost featureless, almost rockless and blanketed with a fine-grained red soil and dark pebbles.
Mission scientists yesterday presented the 360-degree color panorama of the Opportunity landing site in Meridiani Planum. Because the panoramic camera actually consists of two cameras, it produces three-dimensional images. The camera also has 14 color filters, so it can view a scene from the infrared to the blue.
''It provides us with a real sense of 'You Are There' at the site,'' said Dr. Jeffrey R. Johnson, a member of the science team from the United States Geological Survey in Flagstaff, Ariz.
Before the rovers landed, many scientists expected that the Spirit would land on more interesting terrain in Gusev Crater and that the Opportunity would have to drive quite a distance to find worthy objects of study.
''It's just the opposite,'' said Dr. Ronald Greeley, a professor of geological sciences at Arizona State University who is on the science team.
That reaction may seem odd for a mission trying to unravel the geological history of Mars, specifically whether it was once warm and wet.
Gusev Crater may be an ancient lakebed. With river channels visible at its perimeter, water almost certainly flowed into the 95-mile-wide depression, at least intermittently, and the water would have carried rocks from surrounding regions.
The fun at Gusev, geologists say, will be the chance to examine a wide variety of rocks from many places.
''We see rocks there, but we don't really know where they came from,'' said Dr. Steven W. Squyres, a professor of astronomy at Cornell who is the mission's principal investigator. ''Many were probably carried there by water or lava that flowed up. It's going to be a tough puzzle to sort out.''
But Gusev, it turns out, looks like terrain at the two Viking lander sites in the 1970's and what the Mars Pathfinder encountered in 1997.
Scientists hope to head off soon to a more interesting site, a crater 800 feet away, where they hope that the depression discloses more of the geological history below the surface.
The landing site on Meridiani Planum, by comparison, looked so bland and boring from orbit that mission scientists briefly considered asking that the target be nudged to an area with a few more craters.
Now that the Opportunity has landed, scientists are wondering how long they can linger near the landing site. The surreal surroundings look like nothing else. The soil is considerably darker than the other landing sites.
''I always knew if we went to enough places on Mars we would find something that's truly different,'' Dr. Squyres said at a news conference after the landing.
By luck, the Opportunity overshot its target, ending in a shallow 72-foot-wide crater. The scientists gasped when the first photographs showed an outcrop of bedrock 25 feet away, the first piece of Martian bedrock they will be able to explore closely.
The bedrock contains fine layers, as thin as half an inch, indicating that it is sedimentary or layers of volcanic ash from eruptions.
''The beauty of bedrock is you know this is the home neighborhood of these rocks,'' Dr. Squyres said. ''That's just a tremendously valuable thing. Instead of being busted up into pieces, you've actually got these layers.''
Dr. Squyres said the layers are too thin to be lava flows.
An instrument that measures thermal emissions has identified in the dark pebbly surface an iron oxide that on Earth typically forms in the presence of water. The oxide probably gives the surface its dark color.
Even the dirt fascinates scientists. The panoramas show round bright circles where the air bags that cushioned the landing bounced. The soil even shows the imprints of the seams of the air bags.
''Hopefully,'' Dr. Johnson said, ''over the next few weeks as the rover starts to do its reconnaissance of the outcrop and sample some of the soils, we'll have a better idea of just the type of the geological history we're looking at.''
