Federal Panel Hears Testimony on Vaccinations and Autism

Medical experts squared off Monday before a federal panel trying to determine whether a mercury-based preservative once common in routine childhood vaccines was behind the rising rates of autism in the United States.
Most of the epidemiologists who testified said they doubted that the preservative, thimerosal, was responsible. But a few toxicologists said they had become more and more convinced of a potential link.
Since 1999, thimerosal has been gradually removed from vaccines given to infants and toddlers in the United States, though it can still be found in flu shots and others.
While autism is increasing sharply both in the United States and abroad, scientists have been unable to pinpoint a cause. Many suggest that the rise is unlikely to have an environmental cause and can be explained by other factors like rising awareness on the part of parents, doctors and teachers.
Still, some toxicologists told the panel, convened by the Institute of Medicine, that mercury levels were higher in children with autism. They said these children might have biochemical defects that prevented them from processing the metal as efficiently as do normal children.
The idea that thimerosal might be causing autism ''has become more plausible than when your committee first discussed this,'' said Dr. H. Vasken Aposhian, a toxicologist at the University of Arizona.
Another toxicologist, Boyd Haley of the University of Kentucky, told the panel that his studies had shown that testosterone might fuel the toxic effects of mercury. Autism overwhelmingly affects boys.
Epidemiological studies, including a Danish one published last year, have shown no connection between thimerosal exposure and autism.
The federal Centers for Disease Control and Prevention in Atlanta and the American Academy of Pediatrics have said no credible scientific evidence connects thimerosal with autism or other childhood neurological disorders.
The Institute of Medicine panel is collecting data for a report to be issued in June.
At Monday's hearing, the scientists were joined by a vocal group of parents of autistic children who say their children's symptoms, including developmental delays, social inhibition and immune system defects, were caused by a toxic accumulation of mercury from vaccines for pertussis, diphtheria, hepatitis B, and measles, mumps and rubella.
Representative Dave Weldon, Republican of Florida, accused the Centers for Disease Control of ignoring potential links and said it was blocking access by outside researchers to a vaccine database it maintained with a group of managed-care organizations.
''I received numerous complaints that this event is not a further attempt to get at the facts but rather a desire to sweep these issues under the rug,'' said Mr. Weldon, an advocate for parents with autistic children.
Tom Skinner, a spokesman for the disease centers, said the agency's director, Dr. Julie L. Gerberding, had discussed the issue with Mr. Weldon and shared his commitment ''to addressing the importance of autism and vaccine safety with the best possible science and the most effective programs.''
Most of the studies presented to the panel on Monday have been published already, but the hearing gave members a chance to question researchers.
Dr. Frank DeStefano, a researcher at the disease centers, presented a study of schoolchildren in the Atlanta area who were given vaccines that contained thimerosal that found no increased risk of autism. It received widespread attention when it was published last November. But parent groups and Mr. Weldon say the preliminary conclusions of the study, which were circulated among researchers in 2000, suggest a link, and they allege that the data were changed.
Dr. DeStefano said raw data from the study would be made available to other researchers.
Two outsiders who have examined that information, Dr. Mark Geier, a physician, and his son David Geier, who have been expert witnesses for parents seeking payment from the National Vaccine Injury Compensation Program, said they had come to the conclusion that thimerosal was causing autism. ''That database supports every other database that thimerosal is a major contributor to the autism epidemic,'' Mark Geier said.
Correction:  February 26, 2004, Thursday  An article on Feb. 10 about a federal hearing on the relationship between autism and thimerosal, a preservative once common in childhood vaccines, referred incorrectly to a study in the journal Pediatrics that some toxicologists and parent groups have interpreted as suggesting a link. It was published in November, not this month; its subjects were children in several H.M.O.'s in California and Massachusetts, not in the Atlanta area. (A second autism study, carried out in the Atlanta area, appeared in Pediatrics this month.)
