OBSERVATORY

Finding Martian Molecules
The two Viking landers that reached Mars in 1976 carried instruments for analyzing the planet's soil for the presence of organic molecules. For their time, these shoe box-size biochemistry laboratories were marvels of miniaturization and engineering. But they didn't resolve the issue of whether there is or was life on Mars.
In retrospect, they may not have been sensitive enough. The instruments didn't find any significant organic molecules, but given what else was discovered about Mars on those missions, that was hardly surprising. The Martian surface was found to be so reactive that most organic molecules that did exist would be rapidly destroyed. So only instruments with much greater sensitivity than those on the landers would be able to detect the extremely small concentrations of molecules that might remain.
Now, Dr. Richard A. Mathies of the University of California, Berkeley, and colleagues have built such an instrument, designed to detect amino acids. Called the Mars Organic Analyzer and described in The Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, it uses a technique called capillary electrophoresis to separate the molecules and laser-stimulated fluorescence to detect them. It accomplishes all this with microfluidic technology: most of the work is done on a tiny wafer filled with microscopic channels, valves and pumps.
The analyzer was tested on soil from the Atacama Desert in Chile, an extremely dry region that is considered among the most Mars-like places on Earth, and in the Panoche Valley in central California, which has a lot of jarosite, a mineral also found on Mars (and a sign that water once existed there).
In the Chilean samples, amino acids were detected at concentrations as low as 10 parts per billion, while the concentrations in the California samples were even lower -- as low as 70 parts per trillion. The researchers hope to build an analyzer that will be carried aboard the European Space Agency's ExoMars mission, to be launched in 2009.
Giving an Ice Sheet an Age
While the organic analyzer is designed to detect something far away, Dr. Greg Balco of the University of Washington and colleagues have been working to detect something far back in time. Using land-based data, they have determined the age of the first North American glacial maximum -- the first time the Laurentide ice sheet spread down from the north. To date recent glacial maximums, scientists measure the carbon 14 isotope in the rocks that the glaciers deposit at their southernmost extensions before they retreat. But carbon 14 dating doesn't work for very old rocks, so older maximums have been less precisely dated, using marine sediments that just give an idea of the changes in ice volume.
Dr. Balco and his team used a different technique, analyzing rocks in central Missouri for radioactive isotopes of aluminum and beryllium. These are produced by exposure of quartz to cosmic rays when the quartz is on the surface. The production stops when the rock is buried and the isotope decays, enabling scientists to calculate the age of the burial.
The Missouri quartz was buried by all the material dumped by the glacier at the extent of its range. So the date of the burial -- about 2.4 million years ago, the researchers report in the journal Science -- corresponds to the date of the glacial maximum. The researchers say this is the first, and nearly the most southerly, advance of the Laurentide sheet.
A Clogged Passageway
Ice of a different sort has been wreaking havoc in Antarctica. A 100-mile-long iceberg, B15-A, part of an even bigger iceberg that broke off the Ross Ice Shelf five years ago, has drifted into a position where it is affecting wind and water currents in the Ross Sea. As a result, there is more ice than usual in the sea this time of year, creating more headaches for ships supplying the American base at McMurdo Station.
The difficulties may end soon, however, as the berg is drifting toward a glacier, the Drygalski Ice Tongue. A collision, which could happen any day, may break the iceberg and help open the area.
Homing Pigeons, Close to Home
Homing pigeons are renowned for their ability to navigate over long distances, and after decades of study scientists are pretty sure they know how the birds do it. They use their sense of smell to figure out where they are and the position of the sun to determine the direction they must fly.
But less is known about how pigeons navigate when they are close to home, in more familiar surroundings. Many researchers have thought that in such situations the birds must rely, at least partly, on visual cues.
''There's been controversy about whether familiar landmarks have been used,'' said Jessica Meade, a doctoral student in the Animal Behavior Research Group at the University of Oxford in England. ''Because there was no tracking of the birds along the homeward route, the hypotheses aren't very clear.''
Ms. Meade and two colleagues, Dr. Dora Biro and Dr. Tim Guilford, set out to rectify that situation, using small Global Positioning System loggers attached to the backs of 15 homing pigeons. These devices, which weigh about an ounce, use satellite signals to record precise location fixes every second.
The researchers released the birds about three miles from home, and each bird had about 20 flights from the same point. The results are published in Proceedings B, a journal of the Royal Society.
At first, the researchers found, the birds' routes were highly variable. But after a number of flights the birds began to follow the same path from flight to flight, even though they were not necessarily the most direct routes home.
This route stereotypy, as it is called, implies that the birds use visual cues to navigate: they follow the same cues in order to reduce the memory load on their brains.
''We were also surprised that the routes were longer than they needed to be,'' Ms. Meade said. This implies that the pigeons use a chain of landmarks by themselves or in combination with compass bearings, but that they do not integrate direction and distance. If they did, Ms. Meade said, they would realize their routes are not the most efficient ones.
Whatever the precise method, the work suggests that homing pigeons shift from primarily compass navigation to visual navigation when they get near their home.
''It seems like they use a different strategy when they are very familiar with a task,'' Ms. Meade said.
Observatory
