New Vaccine Said to Offer Hope Against Deadly Bacterium

A new vaccine tested in West Africa could save the lives of thousands of poor rural children who die each year from bacterial infections, a team of scientists reported yesterday.
The vaccine is a strengthened version of Prevnar, which has been given widely to American infants since 2000 and prevents rare but serious infections with the Streptococcus pneumoniae bacterium.
In the third world, the same germ is a major killer, and the new vaccine, tested in Gambia, ''exceeded our expectations,'' said Dr. Orin Levine, head of the pneumonia vaccine program at the Global Alliance for Vaccines and Immunization, which backed the trial.
The results are to be published today in The Lancet, a British medical publication.
''No one expected so big a reduction in pneumonia, hospitalization and mortality,'' Dr. Levine said. ''Most people don't know it, but pneumococcal disease kills more people every year than malaria. In this trial, we prevented one death for every 200 children we vaccinated. That's a whopping public-health contribution.''
Susan McKinney, an immunization expert at the United States Agency for International Development, which spends hundreds of millions of dollars on vaccines for poor countries, said her agency was ''delighted'' with the trial. ''The impact this vaccine could have in developing countries is fantastic,'' she said.
How cheaply it can be made remains to be seen, but experts were optimistic yesterday that poor countries would eventually get regular supplies.
Lisa Jacobs, a spokeswoman for the alliance, known as GAVI, said: ''This is exactly the kind of opportunity GAVI is looking for. I can't say definitely that GAVI will fund this -- the board has to make that decision. But given that this data is so promising, we'll definitely look at this.''
The alliance was created in 2000 as a partnership of donor governments, private foundations, the World Health Organization and drug companies to make vaccines broadly available at low cost. It has received $1.5 billion from the Bill and Melinda Gates Foundation, $300 million from the United States and hundreds of millions more from other donors.
In the United States, Prevnar, made by Wyeth Pharmaceuticals of Collegeville, Pa., costs about $250 for a course of four shots -- far more than poor countries can afford or donors will pay.
Natalie deVane, a Wyeth spokeswoman, said the company was negotiating a price for standard Prevnar with the Gambian government and would work with GAVI in the future on the strengthened vaccine.
It is common, several experts said, for vaccine makers to sell at high prices in the West to recoup their research costs, then offer the products at bargain prices in poor countries.
For example, said Dr. Levine, a professor of international health at Johns Hopkins University Medical school, a vaccine used in poor countries that protects against diphtheria, tetanus, whooping cough, hepatitis B and haemophilus influenza B in one shot is purchased by the Global Alliance for $3.65 a dose, a fraction of what similar shots cost in the West.
The vaccine tested in Gambia, made up especially by Wyeth for the trial, had antigens against nine strains of the bacterium. Prevnar has antigens against seven strains. Ms. deVane said Wyeth was now making one with antigens against 13 strains.
It is being tested for safety and for its ability to provoke an immune response, but presumably will not require another $30 million clinical trial in 17,000 children, like the one in Gambia.
Dr. Paul A. Offit, chief of infectious diseases at Children's Hospital in Philadelphia, who was not connected to the study, said the vaccine's 77 percent success rate at preventing diseases caused by the type of bacteria in the vaccine was ''excellent.''
There are 90 strains of Streptococcus pneumoniae, he said, but the majority of infections are caused by a few strains. Prevnar was approved in the United States after it was tested on 38,000 children in northern California.
But vaccines that work in the West often do not work in poor countries with open sewers, tropical heat and urban crowding. In Africa, for example, it can take 10 doses of polio vaccine to achieve the same immunity that three doses will give in the United States because there are so many similar viruses in the African environment that can attach themselves to the same cell receptors as the vaccine.
The chief author of the study, Dr. Felicity Cutts, a professor of epidemiology at Britain's Medical Research Council, said the fact that the vaccine had cut deaths among Gambian children by 16 percent was ''a nice and unexpected result.''
Correction:  March 30, 2005, Wednesday  An article on Friday about a large clinical trial that found the vaccine Prevnar to be effective against deadly bacterial infections among children in West Africa misstated an affiliation for Dr. Orin Levine, executive director of the pneumonia vaccine program at the Global Alliance for Vaccines and Immunization. He is a professor of international health at the Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health, not the Johns Hopkins School of Medicine.
