Health Agency Tightens Rules Governing Federal Scientists

After accusations that some government scientists used their official positions for private gain, the National Institutes of Health announced rules on Thursday that ban its scientists from consulting for drug companies.
''Our research should be based on scientific evidence that is not influenced by any other factors,'' Dr. Elias A. Zerhouni, director of the health institutes, said at a news conference.
The rules are being issued after disclosures that scientists at the institutes leveraged their positions to land lucrative consulting contracts that seemed to conflict with their official duties or at least overlap with them. Those contracts caused some critics to worry that research by the agency could be tainted.
An investigation by the agency concluded that 44 of its 1,200 senior scientists appeared to have violated rules governing consulting and that 9 might have violated criminal laws.
The conflicts were first reported by The Los Angeles Times.
The regulations are not as draconian as those that an internal panel proposed in February. Under those proposals, which caused an uproar, not only was consulting banned, but 6,000 scientists would have also been forced to sell all shares they owned in pharmaceutical and biotechnology companies.
Any remunerative activity outside of work -- even selling jewelry or singing -- would have had to be disclosed and approved by ethics overseers. All 18,000 employees would have been forced to limit their holdings in any one company to shares valued at no more than $15,000.
Under the final rules, the top 200 executives will be required to keep the value of their holdings in any single drug company below $15,000. Some 6,000 other employees will have to submit for review their holdings in such companies. If the holdings are determined to conflict with official responsibilities, the employees will be asked to sell these shares, officials said.
Agency scientists will also be allowed to hold fiduciary positions in medical societies as part of their lives outside the agency, a practice that the proposed rules would have banned.
''Clearly, we do not want to impede the normal academic interactions that scientists need to have with the rest of the world,'' Dr. Zerhouni said.
The changes were welcomed by scientists at the agency who had fiercely criticized the old proposals.
''This is a very good step forward, but it doesn't end the issue,'' said Dr. Ezekial Emanuel, chairman of the executive committee of the Assembly of Scientists, a group that filed a suit against the old rules and then withdrew it.
His group, Dr. Emanuel said, would continue to fight travel bans and bureaucratic inertia that he said is hurting the agency.
The changes disappointed some critics of the pharmaceutical industry's influence on research.
''These rules by no means end the influence of the pharmaceutical industry on N.I.H. employees,'' said Dr. Sidney M. Wolfe, director of the health research group at Public Citizen, the consumer advocacy group.
Dr. Wolfe noted that the new rules let employees deliver medical education lectures paid for by drug companies. Although no strings are supposed to be attached to the financing, Dr. Wolfe noted that scientists who disagreed with the positions of the drug industry were rarely invited to give such lectures.
The controversy surrounding consulting work and scientists' relationships with drug companies has been a black eye for the health institutes, which has for years enjoyed highly favorable press coverage and widespread support on Capitol Hill.
Investigations found that the health institutes had such poor and inconsistent controls over scientists' outside activities that the agency could not even answer investigators' basic questions about the extent of the problem.
One scientist, Dr. P. Trey Sunderland, a senior researcher at the National Institute of Mental Health, received more than $500,000 in consulting fees from Pfizer at the time he was collaborating with the company in his official work of studying patients with Alzheimer's disease.
Despite rules that require government scientists to notify the institutes of their consulting deals, Dr. Sunderland did not make such a report.
Dr. Zerhouni initially dismissed the problems as paperwork issues or the indiscretions of a few people. But as the disclosures built, he proposed modest changes.
Late last year, he proposed a one-year ban on all consulting work while the agency improved controls. Dr. Zerhouni termed the new rules ''the most restrictive of any we know about in the world of biomedical research.''
The revisions were made after officials received more than 1,300 comments, many fiercely critical, on the proposal. Dr. Zerhouni said he was not surprised that so many employees opposed the proposed rules. He said it was always his intent to adapt the new rules after receiving comments from outside.
The rules go into effect on Tuesday. Officials will have to divest their stock portfolios by Jan. 30. Dr. Zerhouni said he intended to re-examine the new rules in a year to make sure they have not had negative effects on the agency's ability to recruit top scientists.
Dr. Zerhouni also said he hoped to spur a broader discussion about conflicts of interest in universities.
