Rotavirus Drugs Deemed Safe and Effective

Two new vaccines against rotavirus, the leading known cause of deaths from diarrhea among infants around the world, have proved safe and effective in two of the largest clinical trials in the history of medicine.
Studies of the two vaccines, one made by Merck and one by GlaxoSmithKline, are to be published today in The New England Journal of Medicine. Each trial enrolled more than 60,000 infants, in part to avoid the fate that befell the last licensed rotavirus vaccine, which was withdrawn seven years ago after it was blamed for dangerous bowel obstructions in 1 in 10,000 children.
''The results to date are very optimistic, very promising,'' said Dr. Samuel L. Katz, a professor of pediatrics at Duke University and former chairman of the federal Advisory Committee on Immunization Practices. ''The real test will be in the global health arena, and if they are as safe and effective as they seem to be, they'll be remarkably helpful.''
The two companies said they were taking their vaccines to rich and poor countries, but with different strategies: the Glaxo vaccine is already in use in Brazil, the Philippines and other developing countries, and it is close to licensing in Europe, but the company has not yet applied to sell it in the United States. The Merck vaccine may be available here as early as spring; then the company will seek licenses in Europe and in some poor countries. Merck and Glaxo say they are starting clinical trials in very poor countries in Africa and Asia.
Globally, rotavirus kills as many as 600,000 children a year -- about half as many as malaria kills -- and the World Health Organization has eagerly sought a vaccine.
Nearly all children everywhere catch the virus by age 5, and most cases are mild. But severe cases can erupt into a combination of watery diarrhea and constant vomiting that leads to severe dehydration. Better diets and intravenous rehydration nearly always save children in the West, and only about 20 children a year die of rotavirus infections in the United States. But about 100,000 die of it in India each year, and 1,000 in Mexico.
Even in the United States, the virus sends 55,000 infants to the hospital each year. Dr. Paul Offit, chief of infectious diseases at Children's Hospital of Philadelphia and one of the developers of the Merck vaccine, said rotavirus symptoms were among the most common causes of admissions to his hospital in winter. He described an infant he knew of who had developed the virus overnight and collapsed into semi-consciousness the next day as her mother was stuck in a traffic jam trying to reach a suburban Philadelphia hospital. The child's veins were so shrunken that a surgeon had to be called to get an intravenous line into a neck vein. ''In Botswana, that child would have died,'' Dr. Offit said.
In 1999, Wyeth pulled its rotavirus vaccine, Rotashield, from the American market after it was blamed for very rare cases of intussusception, in which a section of the gut collapses into itself like a telescope. A child with it may begin screaming in pain and may develop persistent vomiting and produce black stools.
A later National Institutes of Health study argued that Rotashield might not have been responsible -- intussusception can happen spontaneously for unknown reasons -- but by then the damage had been done. Once the vaccine was ruled unsafe for Americans, it was politically impossible to offer it in poor countries, even though it might have saved hundreds of thousands of lives while possibly being to blame for a handful of deaths.
That history was responsible for creating such large clinical trials.
Glaxo's vaccine, called Rotarix, and Merck's, called Rotateq, showed low intussusception rates and no difference between children who got the vaccine and those who got a placebo.
Also, both are oral vaccines using weakened live virus, like the polio vaccine used in poor countries. Such vaccines are easier to use than vaccines requiring needles and may give longer immunity.
Glaxo tested its vaccine on children from poor and middle-income families in Latin America, while Merck's trial was conducted largely in wealthy countries, including the United States and Finland, though it included children in Jamaica and Mexico. The Glaxo vaccine prevented severe rotavirus disease in 85 percent of children while the Merck vaccine prevented it in 98 percent.
But the two vaccines may be equally effective, said Dr. Roger I. Glass, a vaccine specialist at the federal Centers for Disease Control and Prevention in Atlanta, who compared the studies. That is because the two defined ''severe'' slightly differently and because the two test populations were different -- the poorer children in the Glaxo trial were presumably more likely to be malnourished and to have other competing viruses in their intestines, he said.
In what he called ''a particularly exciting finding of great importance to public health,'' both vaccines substantially reduced hospitalization for all diarrheas. That suggests that rotavirus may cause more illness than had been realized -- most diarrhea victims, even in the United States, are never tested to find the cause -- so a vaccine may do much more good than doctors had hoped.
Each vaccine has advantages and disadvantages, specialists said.
Glaxo's is made from a weakened human strain, and is delivered in two doses. Merck's is a bovine strain with bits of genetic material from five human ones. It takes three doses. As a result, the Glaxo vaccine will presumably be cheaper and easier for poor countries.
Global prices are still being negotiated. Brazil offers the vaccine free to all children, so Glaxo sells to the Brazilian government for $15 for the two doses. It sells to the private sector in Mexico for $100 and expects to sell it in Europe for more than $100, Jean Stéphenne, president of Glaxo's vaccine division, said. Prices are ''a function of the G.D.P. of different countries,'' he said, and higher for private doctors than to public clinics. If an agency like the Global Alliance for Vaccines and Immunization that buys for poor countries puts in large enough orders, Mr. Stéphenne said, it might get a price as low as or lower than Brazil's.
Dr. Glass of the disease control centers said the emergence of two effective vaccines was ''wonderful.''
''I've been working on rotavirus for 25 years,'' he said. ''Everyone gets excited about SARS or Ebola or Marburg, but they haven't killed half a million people in a decade, and this is a disease that kills half a million a year.''
