SCIENTIST AT WORK: Randall White; Falling in Love With France and Its Troves of Ancient History

A few miles upstream from this red-roofed village in the Périgord region of southern France, the meandering Vézère River flows past the entrance to the Gorge of Hell. A trail runs along the base of a limestone cliff to a locked steel door. Behind the door, which can be opened to a visitor only by appointment, is the oldest depiction of a fish ever discovered.
About 25,000 years ago, a prehistoric artist carved the yardlong, bas-relief sculpture into the yellowish ceiling of a shallow rock shelter known today as the Abri du Poisson. The image is so vivid and detailed that experts have been able to make out its species, Salmo salar, the Atlantic salmon.
The fish is framed by a rectangular pattern of deep, closely spaced holes, which, according to Périgord lore and guidebooks on sale at the National Museum of Prehistory in Les Eyzies, are the remnants of an abortive attempt by a Swiss archaeologist to remove this precious artwork and sell it to Berlin's prehistory museum.
Conventional accounts of the episode, which dates to 1912, maintain that this treachery was stopped just in time by the valiant efforts of French prehistorians led by Denis Peyrony, a local schoolteacher who founded the Les Eyzies museum and conducted some of the Périgord's most important archaeological digs.
On a crisp evening in March, however, the archaeologist Randall White of New York University stood at the lectern of the museum's 126-seat auditorium and told the capacity crowd a very different story. The Swiss archaeologist, Otto Hauser, was innocent, Dr. White argued, the victim of an ugly press campaign that included vicious anti-Semitic and anti-German slurs, even though Hauser was neither Jewish nor German.
As Dr. White maintains in his new book in French on the scandal, ''L'Affaire de L'Abri du Poisson,'' the attempted abduction of the fish was carried out entirely by local French citizens, including the owner of the surrounding land.
As for Peyrony, Dr. White concluded that he was not such a steadfast champion of France's cultural heritage after all. In the midst of the Hauser affair, Peyrony, who died in 1954, sold 1,200 prehistoric artifacts from his Périgord excavations to the American Museum of Natural History in New York for a sum equal to about twice his annual schoolteacher's salary.
Dr. White's book on the affair, which is based on five years of research in French, German and American archives, is the culmination of more than three decades of archaeological work in France, during which he has become one of the world's leading experts on the cave paintings, sculptures, carved figurines, and necklaces and other personal ornaments that prehistoric humans produced here by the thousands.
''He has done a huge amount to clarify the unique and unprecedented nature of Cro-Magnon behavioral expression,'' says Ian Tattersall, anthropology curator for the Museum of Natural History. ''His research has allowed us to understand what a break with the past it truly represented.''
Currently, Dr. White is director of an international team excavating at the 35,000-year-old site of Abri Castanet in the Vézère Valley, which was first investigated by Peyrony and has provided some of the earliest evidence for the dispersal of Homo sapiens from Africa to Western Europe.
Peyrony found hundreds of personal ornaments and dozens of paintings and engravings at Abri Castanet. Dr. White's new excavations, financed by the National Science Foundation, are intended to address several unanswered questions about these first migrations of modern humans, including how and why they replaced the Neanderthals who had lived in the area for tens of thousands of years.
Meanwhile, Dr. White himself has become an ardent defender of France's cultural heritage and a fierce opponent of the antiquities trade. In early 2006, for example, he publicly protested the $200 million donation from the antiquities collector Shelby White (no relation) to N.Y.U. that is to be used to create a new Institute for the Study of the Ancient World, on the ground that some objects in Ms. White's collection are alleged to have come from illicit excavations.
His work on personal ornaments has taken him to museums all over the world, but particularly in the United States and Canada, where he has studied and published analyses of artifacts from France that had languished for decades in dusty drawers. Over the years, he has made France his second home, putting down deep roots in the country and its culture. He spends several months each year in the Périgord. Recently, he bought a stone farmhouse and several other buildings on 113 acres of land just outside Les Eyzies, which he shares with his longtime French companion, Hélène Talenton, who owns a beauty salon in a nearby community.
Dr. White is ''well accepted by the French archaeological community,'' said Alain Turq, curator of the Les Eyzies museum. ''He lives here and he speaks our language very well, which is very important.''
Today, the Périgord region is probably best known to tourists for its truffles, foie gras and wine. But during the Upper Paleolithic period, about 10,000 to 40,000 years ago, the caves and rock shelters carved out by the Vézère and its tributaries some two million years earlier were buzzing with artistic activity.
A dozen miles upstream from Les Eyzies, prehistoric artists were painting the magnificent images of bulls, horses, reindeer and rhinoceroses at Lascaux Cave. Just north of the town, 19th-century archaeologists found a rich trove of art and bone tools, including the head of a mammoth carved on a piece of ivory, in a rock shelter called La Madeleine, which gave its name to the so-called Magdalenian culture that marks the epitome of the Upper Paleolithic in France.
Between these two sites, at Le Moustier, Hauser in 1908 found the skull of a Neanderthal adolescent, along with characteristic Neanderthal stone tools from what is now referred to as the Mousterian culture.
Dr. White, 54, who was born and grew up in Canada's Alberta Province and has maintained his Canadian nationality, came to the Périgord in 1974 while an undergraduate anthropology student at the University of Alberta.
''I fell in love with southern France, its archaeology, and its ambience,'' he said. ''I discovered that I was a francophile.''
For his doctoral thesis at the University of Toronto, Dr. White conducted the first topographical survey of all the 180 known Upper Paleolithic sites in the region. ''I still get calls from people asking where is this or that site,'' he said.
Dr. White was hired by N.Y.U. in 1981, and the next year published a paper in the journal Current Anthropology that made his reputation. In that and subsequent publications, he has argued that modern humans were able to replace Neanderthals in Europe not necessarily because they had superior cognition, but because they developed long-range social networks that allowed them to better adapt to local conditions.
The dramatic explosion of art in Upper Paleolithic Europe, and especially the creation of uniformly designed personal ornaments that early humans seemed to use to identify themselves as part of the same group -- behaviors that Neanderthals engaged in only minimally, at best -- allowed the Homo sapien newcomers to out-compete their rivals, Dr. White maintained.
His ideas have been challenged by archaeologists who think that Neanderthal symbolic expression has been underestimated, as well as by researchers who think that the supposed ''explosion'' is really a continuation of nascent symbolic behavior in Africa going back at least 75,000 years. Nevertheless, Dr. Tattersall of the Museum of Natural History says, Dr. White's work has demonstrated that ''the Upper Paleolithic is a remarkable period, as much for the density and vividness of its creative manifestations as for the contrasts it provides with the cultures that preceded it.''
Despite Dr. White's early success, he found it difficult to begin a dig of his own in the Périgord. Dr. White says that the French prehistorian responsible for issuing permits to excavate in the area preferred that he work as part of his team rather than independently.
''I was shut out of working in France the way I wanted to do it,'' Dr. White said. Rather than agree to work as part of the team, he began to look at collections of artifacts stored in museums in Canada and the United States, where he found thousands of objects from digs by Peyrony and other archaeologists, including artifacts from the Abri Castanet, sometimes stored in terrible conditions.
''I saw Upper Paleolithic engravings with drawers on top of them,'' Dr. White said, adding that these experiences fueled his early anger about the antiquities trade.
In the late 1970s, Dr. White had met René Castanet, a local landowner and the son of one of the region's most celebrated amateur archaeologists, Marcel Castanet, after whom the Abri Castanet was named. The two men soon developed a close friendship. In the mid-1990s, when Dr. White applied for permission to reopen excavations at Abri Castanet, he now had two things going for him: ''an enormous credibility from all the research I had done,'' he said, and his relationship with René Castanet, who owned the land the rock shelter sat on and whose permission was necessary to dig there.
Getting his own site to dig sealed Dr. White's reputation in French archaeology and gave him the foothold he needed to indulge his interests in the history of the French antiquities trade as well as to challenge conventional accounts of the Hauser affair.
The five years he spent researching his book ''was the work of a monk,'' says Alain Roussot, who was curator of the Museum of the Aquitaine in Bordeaux from 1962 to 2000 and has known Dr. White since he first starting working in France. Dr. Roussot, who helped correct Dr. White's French text, adds that his investigation was ''very meticulous.''
Yet not everyone in the Périgord is ready to accept all of Dr. White's conclusions about Peyrony and the fish. ''Things were more complicated back then,'' said Dr. Turq of the Les Eyzies museum. ''Hauser made no permanent contributions to French archaeology, while Peyrony invested his money in excavations and built the museum in Les Eyzies. It was a different time.''
Scientist at Work | Randall White
