RYAN HOWARD, NO ASTERISK

What would it feel like to inhabit the role that so many have auditioned for across the decades, on ballfields in all 50 states and beyond? Back foot dug into the batter's box, the grip on the bat firm but relaxed. The baseball approaches as if in slow motion, and you start your swing with a short stride, a subtle shift of weight and a powerful forward thrust of the hips. Your hands follow and then, finally, the barrel of the bat comes whipping through the hitting zone and -- crack! -- connects with the ball, sending it on a majestic arc into the upper deck.
Just once, right? To be that most American of sports icons: the Slugger.
Now, here is Ryan Howard of the Philadelphia Phillies on Sept. 3, 2006. He is a baby in baseball years, still in his first full big-league season, but a man-child at the plate: 6-foot-4, 250-plus pounds and big all over. He has biceps that it would take two large hands to fully encircle, thick-muscled forearms and -- more noticeable in the locker room than on the field, where he wears a baggy uniform top -- a surprisingly ample midsection. Howard is Ruthian, only bigger. Even his round, expressive face -- quick to break into a smile, more open and inviting than the typical impassive countenance of the big-time pro athlete -- seems extra large.
He takes his place in the left batter's box at Citizens Bank Park in Philadelphia, a hitter's paradise -- not that the dimensions of a ballpark matter much to him. Legend has it that Howard hit his first 400-foot home run at age 12, a blast that rocketed over an outfield fence and smacked against the side of a Red Lobster restaurant.
On this Sunday afternoon, the opposing pitcher is Tim Hudson of the Atlanta Braves, a veteran with stuff that is more clever than overpowering. Hudson's pitches have what is called late movement -- they sink, dart and sail, leaving hitters waving at air or topping harmless ground balls.
Howard, batting cleanup, leads off the bottom of the second inning. He has, at this point, 49 home runs, an astonishing number for early September. He has already surpassed the team record for home runs in a season, held by Hall of Famer Mike Schmidt, and he is two away from Ralph Kiner's mark for second-year players, set in 1947. (Howard became a full-time big leaguer in July 2005.)
The act of hitting a baseball is an energy transfer: from the body to the bat to the ball. Just before Hudson rocks into his wind-up, Howard, a lefty, uses his right hand to point his 34-ounce bat at a 45-degree angle directly over the pitcher's head. This is a timing device, although, as Howard has become one of the game's most prodigious home-run hitters, it can easily be taken as a boast. Follow the angle of the bat and it suggests a trajectory straight out over the center-field fence.
He brings the bat back as Hudson readies, grips it with both hands and cocks his left (back) elbow. His focus now is on ''staying quiet,'' as he puts it -- being still. He wants no energy to leak out until it can be put to its proper use. His knees are flexed, his weight set back in his stance. Only his wrists are moving, just slightly, causing the top of the bat to wave like a flag in a limp breeze.
The first pitch is a slider, bearing in on Howard's shoe tops. He explodes out of his stance and brings the barrel of the bat down solidly on the ball -- sending a towering drive over the right-center-field wall. Home run No. 50.
Hudson stands at the back of the mound and looks toward the outfield long after the ball has cleared the wall. He stares at the replay on the scoreboard, as if thinking to himself, He hit that pitch where?
Second at-bat: Hudson throws his first pitch near Howard's head, which he casually avoids by leaning back. ''No big deal,'' Howard tells me later. ''You kind of have to expect that.'' After a foul ball, he sends Hudson's third offering -- a fat pitch about belt high -- deep over the center-field wall, in the same general direction as the first one, only quite a bit farther. Home run No. 51.
Third at-bat: With the count at one ball and two strikes Hudson throws a sinker that veers low and away, a pitch that is meant to tempt Howard to swing at something he can't reach -- or, if he does, can't hit solidly. Howard extends his massive arms and hits a line drive to left field, which clears the wall nearly as quickly as a spectator can locate it with his eyes. Home run No. 52.
Three at-bats. Three home runs.
Out on the mound, Hudson looks more bemused than angry. He had put that last pitch right where he intended. ''You kind of scratch your head after that,'' he tells reporters gathered at his locker after the game. ''What the hell are you going to do next?''
Ryan Howard felt a surge of pleasure when he connected on those three swings. He heard the crowd's roar, knew for sure that the second two balls would clear the outfield walls. (The first just cleared the fence, and Howard had taken off hard toward first base out of the batter's box.) But there was a lack of actual physical sensation, or at least one that is easily described -- that weird nothingness of hitting a ball, with force and perfect timing, right on the sweet spot of a baseball bat.
It is an odd neurological loop: job well done, but you know it only because there's no unpleasant message to the contrary. ''You feel a lot more in your hands if the pitch gets in on you and busts you in the handle,'' Howard says. ''It stings. But when you catch it square, it doesn't seem like you feel it as much.''
Last season, Howard had 58 home runs, a total exceeded by only five men in baseball history -- Barry Bonds, Mark McGwire, Sammy Sosa, Roger Maris and Babe Ruth. Twenty-eight of Howard's home runs either tied the game or put the Phillies ahead, and he knocked in a major-league-leading 149 runs -- including 42 in August, the most r.b.i. by a player in a single month in 34 years. He was the National League player of the month in both August and September, and after the season, he was voted the league's Most Valuable Player.
As every baseball fan knows, the game is awash in statistics, some more telling than others. One esoteric stat is particularly enlightening in Howard's case: his home-run-to-fly-ball ratio of 39.5 percent. What that means is that of every 10 fair balls he hits in the air, about 4 end up as home runs. The player with the next highest ratio last year, Travis Hafner of the Cleveland Indians, had a ratio of 30.2.
There is a feast-or-famine aspect to Howard's hitting: he strikes out a lot -- 181 times last season, the second most in the majors -- so he doesn't put as many balls in play as others do in the same number of at-bats. But as his teammate Aaron Rowand says: ''When he hits it, he hits it. Ryan doesn't hit a lot of bloopers.''
The majority of Howard's home runs went to left or center field, the mark of a hitter who is powerful enough not to have to pull balls to reach the seats, and several landed in places rarely reached by batted balls. Last April in Philadelphia, Howard hit a dead-center-field home run that was measured at 496 feet.
It is impossible, of course, to think about power hitting these days without wondering about performance-enhancing drugs. Bonds, McGwire and Sosa all played in what is now commonly called baseball's Steroid Era, and suspicion has fallen on each of them. On the subject of sports and chemical enhancement, the first rule is never to assume guilt -- or innocence. Surprises lurk. But Howard, big from the womb, a lifelong slugger, is generally assumed around baseball to be clean. (Howard is subject to Major League Baseball's drug-testing policy, which calls for players to be tested for steroids, amphetamines and certain other substances once in spring training and at least one other time during the season. He was also tested in the minor leagues.)
In mid-September, a ball hit by Howard at Minute Maid Park in Houston caromed off the glove of a 10-year-old fan in the left-field seats and fell back into the outfield. Television replays clearly showed that it should have been called a home run, but the third-base umpire ruled the ball in play. After the game, Astros first baseman Lance Berkman had an interesting reaction, telling reporters, ''I hope it doesn't cost him the steroid-free home run record.''
It didn't. Howard would have fallen short of Maris's 61 home runs, anyway -- mainly because he became so terrifying to opposing managers that they started walking him at every possible opportunity. He was second in the majors with 37 intentional walks, several of them issued in situations that rarely call for such a move.
For example, in a late-September game, Frank Robinson, then managing the Washington Nationals, twice ordered Howard to be walked in extra innings -- once with the bases empty and two outs, another time with a runner on first who then moved into scoring position as a potential game-winning run. After a game the night before, during which Robinson challenged Howard in a key spot, Robinson told me: ''Every hitter has vulnerabilities. No reason not to attack them.'' When I asked him the next night why he seemed to lose courage, he said: ''Didn't want to press my luck. Ryan is a very strong young man.''
Physicists who have studied hitting toss around terms like ''bat speed,'' ''torque'' and ''rotational mechanics.'' It is fair to say that strength generally promotes bat speed and home-run power. Howard comes from a family of big people and, by appearance, is what used to be called ''country strong.''
Howard and I met one day near his off-season home, in suburban St. Louis, amid a landscape of tract houses and what looked like an endless expanse of strip shopping centers and chain restaurants. He had just finished one of his three-hour, five-times-a-week workouts, which consist mostly of weight training. He had been dieting, too, eating more vegetables and fewer fried foods.
We took a seat at the restaurant he chose, a place called O'Charley's, which featured an oversize menu of American favorites. When his grilled chicken was put down in front of him, he looked displeased and immediately lifted it with his fork. ''I sure hope they put my mashed potatoes under there,'' he said. When he came upon a mound of them, he brightened up. He continued stabbing at a bowl of tortilla chips, loading them up with salsa. ''Do me a favor,'' he told me. ''Eat some of these. Help me out. I'm trying to be good.''
Howard's power surge at the end of last season brought about something unprecedented in recent baseball history. By July, the Phillies had surrendered the season -- and sort of the next one, too. The general manager, Pat Gillick, had traded off important players -- the starting right fielder and third baseman, a starting pitcher, a key left-handed relief pitcher -- and told the team's fans not to expect the Phillies to be contenders until 2008. Such housecleaning happens every season in baseball: lesser teams build for the future by trading veterans for prospects.
What doesn't happen is what the Phillies did next, which was to climb back into the playoff race, largely on the back of Howard, who in the season's second half hit .355 with 30 home runs and 78 r.b.i. By August, Gillick had reversed course and was acquiring veteran talent for the stretch run. (The Phillies were finally eliminated from the wild-card playoff spot on the last weekend of the season.)
Howard, respectful of baseball custom, strives for modesty. Understatement is a much-admired quality in baseball. When I talked to him about the home-run-to-fly-ball ratio, he had no idea what his was (or that anyone even kept such a stat). But when I asked him to guess how many of his fly balls cleared the fences, his answer seemed like a true measure of his estimation of his own abilities. ''I don't know,'' he said. ''Six out of 10? Seven out of 10?''
In some ways, Howard is the anti-Barry Bonds, who looms over the coming baseball season like an unwelcome guest at a dinner party. Bonds, an outfielder with the San Francisco Giants, is 22 home runs from surpassing Hank Aaron's record of 755. For a great many baseball fans, his grim pursuit will be a cause for dismay more than celebration. Even before the steroid allegations, Bonds was one of the game's sour personalities, unloved by fans outside his home city and often reviled by his own teammates.
Howard, by contrast, is cordial with the press, well liked in the clubhouse and much more likely to offer fans a smile and an autograph than a scowl. He arrives early for games and can usually be found with his big frame folded into an easy chair or couch in front of a large TV, watching videos with teammates. He gets high marks for his ''demeanor.'' Baseball people use the word constantly, and it serves as a catchall for many things: a player's work habits; his ability to stay on a steady emotional keel whether he has hit a couple of home runs or struck out four times; his relationships among teammates and coaches.
''Ryan is just a very easy guy to be around,'' the Phillies' manager, Charlie Manuel, says. ''You couldn't ask for a guy with a better demeanor.''
Howard, though, does share one similarity with Bonds, a significant one within the context of baseball's changing sociology: he is an African-American player at a moment when the number of American-born blacks in the major leagues has dropped strikingly. In 2005, the National League champion Houston Astros had no black players on their World Series roster, the first time that was the case for a team in half a century. At one point last season, six teams in Major League Baseball did not have a single black player on their rosters. Below the professional level, there are so few blacks in the game that many of the nation's historically black colleges are fielding baseball teams made up mostly of white and Hispanic players. (The Washington Post reported that Coppin State University in Baltimore had 30 white male students enrolled in 2006; roughly half of them were on the baseball team.)
Black players now make up about 9 percent of big-league rosters -- down from 19 percent in 1995 and 25 percent in 1975. Hispanics, at 29 percent, have become the dominant minority in the game.
So how did Ryan Howard become a baseball player? Part of the answer is that he comes from where many of the game's white players do -- a largely white suburb. He grew up in Wildwood, Mo., on the outer edge of St. Louis's western sprawl. His mother, Cheryl, now retired, worked in marketing, and his father, Ron, is a manager for I.B.M. He has three siblings, including a fraternal twin, all of whom are college-educated professionals.
Ron and Cheryl Howard don't consider themselves particularly athletic. ''I could play everything, just not well,'' Ron told me. Cheryl Howard added: ''I'm from the pre-Title IX days, so I didn't get a chance to play organized sports. But my father played sandlot baseball with Willie Mays in Birmingham, so we've decided Ryan's baseball talent comes through my side.''
When Ryan Howard was 2, his father walked into a room where a TV was showing a baseball game and saw his son intent on the action and swinging a little red bat. ''It was such a natural swing,'' Ron Howard says. ''At that moment I knew he'd be some kind of baseball player. How far? I didn't know. But that feeling came over me.''
To be blessed with hand-eye coordination and the strength to mash a baseball 500 feet ought to fill a man with self-assurance. But pro sports are full of gifted players with cracks in their psyches who on some career-killing level do not fully believe in themselves. Howard's upbringing seems to have imbued him with a sense of self that extends well beyond his abilities on the ball field.
As his parents describe it, their household was a mix of old-time Southern values and middle-class aspiration. ''All our kids were taught to say 'Yes, sir,' 'Yes, ma'am' and so on,'' Ron Howard says. ''We valued hard work and taught them: believe in oneself, believe in each other and believe in the Almighty.''
There were, as well, some quirkier rules. For example, Ron taught everyone to drive using a standard shift, which he considers an essential life skill, and made them take their driving tests in a car with a stick shift. ''No, they weren't pleased about it,'' he recalls, ''but it was a binary situation. You do it this way if you want to drive -- or the other way if you don't want to drive.''
Howard played a lot of soccer as a kid. He was a good high school basketball player. He also played the trombone in the school band. He played a little football, but his mother insisted he give it up because she believed he risked injury by being such a large target.
Ryan Howard says that he was one of just a handful of black players on most of his youth baseball teams. His sports heroes were Barry Bonds, Ken Griffey Jr., Tony Gwynn. ''I guess you can throw Michael in there,'' he adds, meaning Michael Jordan, but he makes it sound like an obligation. He was focused on baseball.
In Philadelphia, Howard faces the particular challenge of playing for a team with famously demanding (and sometimes abusive) fans -- and in a city with a particularly shameful history of mistreating black baseball players. The Phillies were the last team in the National League to sign a black player -- in 1957, a full decade after Jackie Robinson's debut with the Brooklyn Dodgers. Robinson himself suffered such abuse from the Phillies that he later wrote that they were ''a Northern team that I had come to associate with the Deep South.''
Other than Howard, the Phillies have had just one black superstar: Dick Allen, then known as ''Richie,'' a fearsome slugger but a rebel and a turbulent soul who endured such mind-bending abuse from the home crowd that after six years in Philadelphia he was scratching cryptic messages with his spikes in the infield dirt. (Among them, ''Mom,'' ''Boo'' and ''Oct. 2,'' the date of the last game of the 1969 season.)
Sometimes, though, a certain athlete and a city just seem like a good match. Howard drives a GMC Yukon with 100,000-plus miles and is not much for fancy clothes or late nights. His Everyman persona has appeal in a city where even white-collar, well-heeled season-ticket holders are apt to describe themselves as blue-collar fans. During the season, he lives in a condominium in South Philadelphia not far from the ballpark.
''I'm cool with everybody,'' says Howard, who is single and has a 6-year-old son from a former relationship. ''The fans have been nothing but nice to me. I'll walk around the city and people will come up to me and say 'Hi' or 'Keep up the good work' or whatever, and I'll stop and talk to them.''
Baseball is the most hidebound of American sports. It manufactures and honors tradition, myth and superstition. And it probably also has a greater share of ignorance than other sports. The entire movement toward once-obscure and newly developed statistics, after all -- begun by Bill James and others, some of them now in the employ of big-league teams -- came about because professional baseball people drew erroneous conclusions from the same old numbers they loved so much.
A certain amount of ignorance, on the part of baseball executives, most likely impeded Ryan Howard's baseball progress. A man his size is not easily overlooked. But his career trajectory strongly suggests that his talent was underappreciated. He was not a coveted prospect out of high school and went to Southwest Missouri State to play baseball. After the Phillies selected him in the fifth round of the 2001 draft, he began a slow, four-and-a-half-season climb through the minor leagues, making stops in five different minor-league towns and hitting for power and a decent average in each of them.
In 2004, splitting time between Double A and Triple A, he hit 46 home runs and knocked in 131 runs, the kind of performance that ought to bring about a promotion to the big leagues -- especially considering that Howard was already 24. But the Phillies had a veteran at first base, Jim Thome, to whom they had paid millions as a free agent, and Howard began the 2005 season in Scranton, Pa., back in Triple A.
Thome was signed after Howard had already been a Phillies minor leaguer for two seasons; another team, recognizing what it had in Howard, might have spent its free-agent money elsewhere to avoid a logjam at first base. But the Phillies, with no postseason appearances since 1993, have not been the canniest of franchises.
From his parents, who lived through the civil rights struggle in Birmingham and often talked to their children about that era, Howard already knew something about patience and perspective. He didn't much like being stuck in the minor leagues, but knew it wasn't the worst thing that could happen to a person. ''I learned what I could,'' he says of his years in the minors. His father says: ''We didn't see a frustration on Ryan's part. We saw a strong determination.''
After Thome suffered a season-ending injury, Howard finally secured a full-time spot with the Phillies in 2005 -- and hit 22 home runs and earned the National League Rookie of the Year award while playing just a little over half a season. A player who can accomplish that at age 25 -- then follow it up with the season Howard had last year -- almost certainly could have held his own in the big leagues a couple of years earlier. And Howard's extended time in the minors cost him money. His salary last season was $355,000, a pittance by baseball's current economics. He is still a year from arbitration, and can't become a free agent until after the 2011 season, when he will be 32. He has not publicly made an issue of his contract, but recently he switched to a more prominent agent.
In one sense, though, Howard was probably lucky to end up with the Phillies, whose manager, Charlie Manuel, while not much admired for his in-game strategy, is widely considered to have a deep knowledge of hitting. Howard was still in the low minor leagues when Manuel, then an assistant in the Phillies' front office, first saw him bat. Manuel noticed something unusual about Howard's style: he stood way off the plate, and his posture was oriented toward foul ground in left field, like a golfer who compensates for a wicked slice by aiming wide of the fairway.
In Howard's case, he did not like to handle pitches inside, in on his hands, and his strength still allowed him to hit outside pitches a long way. So he took a stance that forced pitchers to throw the ball about a foot inside the plate to jam him. Manuel saw Howard hit a home run to left field and concluded that because of the way he was standing, it was more like a center- or right-field home run -- he had to pull the ball just to keep it fair.
''We got him straightened out a little bit, so it wasn't so extreme,'' Manuel says. ''He was the type of kid you always could talk to.''
All hitters, though, have a way they want to hit, a style that feels natural. Howard's left-field orientation is still a large part of his approach. When he hits the ball to the left of second base, he almost always lifts it, which is what pitchers specifically try to avoid with home-run hitters: fly balls. When he pulls the ball, he hits more ground balls and low line drives with top spin -- the type that do not carry over fences. ''The amazing thing is, even with all those home runs, Ryan's still learning to pull it,'' says Milt Thompson, the Phillies' hitting coach. ''When he learns to clear his hips out of there and get the ball in the air, you'll really see something.''
Pitchers defeat hitters with good pitches, of course, but all hitters have a way they get themselves out, the most common being a lack of patience. Instead of hoarding their energy -- their ''load'' or ''power load,'' as it is called in baseball -- they commit to a swing too soon, particularly on off-speed pitches, and by the time the bat meets the ball they have expended much of their power.
Howard is different. When he gets himself out, it is more often the result of an overabundance of patience. He lets the ball get too close to his body and does not get the barrel of the bat fully around it. ''It's unusual in any player, let alone a big strong kid just into the league,'' Manuel says. ''But that's why Ryan hits the ball the way he does. He's rarely out in front of where he wants to be. He's got his full load intact when he does make contact.''
Howard takes a slight uppercut, quick and compact. ''Ted Williams used to say, The longer the arc, the farther the ball will go,'' Manuel says. ''I say, The longer the arc, the slower the swing. Ryan has all the power he needs with that shorter arc.''
After Howard and I were finished eating at O'Charley's and the table was cleared, I unpacked my laptop and we watched a sort of greatest-hits collection, a compilation of his home runs that the Phillies had copied onto a DVD. He enjoyed it -- what player wouldn't? -- but what struck me was how much he remembered. He came to the plate 704 times last season and saw 2,859 pitches, yet now he recalled pitch sequences from months before. He doesn't keep a notebook, as some hitters do, but it seems he doesn't have to.
''This is a pretty good AB,'' he said as we watched him step in for his at-bat against the New York Mets' Guillermo Mota. ''He was mixing it up pretty good. Fastballs, change-ups, inside, outside.'' After eight pitches, including several foul balls, the count was full. Mota threw a change-up, and Howard barely managed to foul it off. ''That was a tough pitch -- nasty,'' he said. ''Here comes the fastball now.'' The next pitch was indeed a fastball, which Howard hit over the center-field fence for his 47th home run.
Not surprisingly, considering he is the son of a computer programmer, Howard talks about hitting as if each at-bat is a problem to be solved: ''If the pitcher is one you've faced before, you have to be thinking, How did he try to get me out? He might try something different this time, but you have to have that in the back of your mind. Each at-bat and each pitch you have a game plan that comes about from processing all the information you have.''
Mike Arbuckle, who is in charge of the Phillies' minor-league system, told me: ''Ryan has the aptitude and the intelligence to maximize all that natural ability he has. To be honest with you, there are more guys who aren't that way than are. And he also has the inner drive to want to apply all that intelligence, and that's not always the case, either.''
The DVD included Howard's big game against Tim Hudson. After we watched the last home run, the line drive to left field, Howard said he would have had no idea, as he swung, that the pitch was outside. ''That's the point at which you can't be thinking about anything,'' he said. ''You have a game plan, but then it's instinct. You just see the pitch and go after it.''
The camera followed Howard into the dugout after that last home run, then back out onto the top step, where he waved to acknowledge the home crowd's standing ovation. Together, we were watching him at a moment of maximum glory -- the Slugger in full -- but he seemed to want to deflect attention from himself, to display, as always, proper baseball demeanor.
In the background, we caught a glimpse of Phillies shortstop Jimmy Rollins, who seemed to be laughing with a kind of wide-eyed, can-you-believe-this expression on his face. ''Look at Jimmy,'' Ryan Howard said, his own face breaking into a grin. ''He seems like he got a big kick out of that, doesn't he?''
Michael Sokolove is a frequent contributor to Play.
